<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<divisions>
    <dhaka>
        <place id="1">
            <name>National monument at savar</name>
            <address>National Martyrs' Monument, Dhaka-Aricha Hwy, Savar, Dhaka, Dhaka Division, Bangladesh</address>
            <detail>The National Martyrs' Monument at Savar, near Dhaka (35, km. from Dhaka city) is a vey beautiful sight. It takes about an hour fom the Dhaka city. This memorial designed by architect Moinul Hossein, is dedicated to the sacred memory of the millions of unknown martyrs of the 1971 war of liberation.</detail>
            <open>Its free for everyone, no entry fee requires. This is open from morning to sun set. Staying at night time is not allowed by the authority.</open>
            <image>resource/national memorial.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="2">
            <name>Lalbagh Fort</name>
            <address>Lalbagh,Old Dhaka</address>
            <detail>Lalbagh Fort was built in 1678 A.D. by Prince Mohammad Azam, son of Mughal emperor Aurangazeb. The fort has witnessed a bloody battle during the first war of independence (1857) in India when some sepoys here backed by the people revolted against British forces. Bangladesh was then a part of India. In this Fort one finds the tomb of Pari Bibi (Fairy lady), Lalbagh Mosque, Audience Hall.</detail>
            <open>Entry Permits BDT 10 (for local) BDT 100 (for foreigner) Opening time 10.00 AM in Summer (1st April to 30th September) (*Friday opens at 10 AM) 9.00 AM in WInter (1st October to 30th March) (*Friday opens at 9.00 AM) Closing time 6.00 PM in Summer (1st April to 30th September) (*Friday closes at 3.00 PM) 5.00 PM in Winter (1st October to 30th March) Holiday Sunday</open>
            <image>resource/lalbag fort.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="3">
            <name>Central Shaheed Minar</name>
            <address>Dhaka University ,Shahbag,Dhaka.(beside Dhaka Medical college)</address>
            <detail>The Central Shahid Minar in Dhaka is a monument in honour of the language martyrs of 1952. On February 21, 1952, many students and political activists were killed as Pakistani police force opened fire on some protesters who were demanding equal status to their mothe tongue, Bengali. The place was near Dhaka Medical College and Ramna Park in Dhaka. The minar has five pillas made of pure marble stone upon a 14 feet high stage. The bounday on both sides contains lines from poems of famous poets engaved in iron letters.As recognisation of the language movement UN declear 21 February as International mother language day in 1999, which </detail>
            <open>Entry Permits/Fees No. open for visit</open>
            <image>resource/Central shaheed minar.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="4">
            <name>Sonargaon</name>
            <address>Sonargaon, Narayanganj, Dhaka</address>
            <detail>About 27 km. from Dhaka, Sonargaon is the oldest capitals of Bengal. It was the seat of Deva Dynasty until the 13th century. From then onward till the advent of the Mughals, Sonargaon was subsidiary capital of the Sultanate of Bengal during 16th and 17th century. Among the ancient monuments still intact are the Tomb of Sultan Ghiasuddin (1399-1409A.D), the shrines of Panjpirs and Shah Abdul Alla and a beautiful mosque in Goaldi village. The ancient capital of Bangle was called 'Panam Nagar' which is still standing with its past.</detail>
            <open>Entry Permits/Fees BDT 15 (for local) BDT 100 (for foreigner) Opening time Foundation premises : 9.00 AM Museum : 9:30 AM Closing time Foundation premises : 5.00 PM Museum : 4:30 PM ( *Friday keeps close: 12:30 PM to 2:30 PM ) Holiday Wednesday, Thrusday</open>
            <image>resource/Sonargaon.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="5">
            <name>Liberation War Museum</name>
            <address>05, Segun Bagicha, Dhaka, Bangladesh</address>
            <detail>This museum has a very moving display on the1971 War of Independence, with lots of English and Bangla newspaper reports, photographs (some quite graphic ) and memorabilia . The lines on the floor take you on a chronological tour of the conflict. It's one of the best museums in the country.This is the first museum under private initiative and functions very well with good management. In the courtyard there is a cosy cafeteria.</detail>
            <open>Entry Permits/Fees BDT 5.Opening time 10:00 AM.Closing time In Summer : 6:00 PM In Winter: 5:00 PM.Holiday Sunday</open>
            <image>resource/Liberation war museum.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="6">
            <name>Gurdwara Nanak Shahi</name>
            <address>Gurdwara Nanak Shahi,Nilkhet Road ,Ramna DHAKA(near teachers students centre ,Dhaka University)</address>
            <detail>This Sikh temple is out of few still found in Bangladesh and is administered from India. There is no resident Sikh community left in Bangladesh but in recent years has been a good number of Sikh visitors mostly on work in Bangladesh.The gurudwara was founded by a missionary sent to Bangladesh by Baba Gurditta, Son of Guru Hargobind (6th Guru) within 17th century and was completed in 1830. Religiouscelebrations include weekly prayers every friday.Social functions such as Baisakhi arecelebrated. Old relics-an old handwritten volume of Guru Granth Sahib, a copy of the Portrait of Guru Teg Bahadur are preserved here.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Gurdwara Nanak Shahi.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="7">
            <name>Dhakeshwari Temple</name>
            <address>Dhakeshwari Kali Temple, Amimpur, Old Dhaka(Beside BUET), Bangladesh</address>
            <detail>This is the oldest Hindu temple in Dhaka City (12th century). The meaning of the name is "Temple of the Goddess of Dhaka". Legend has it that the city of Dhaka was named after this temple. The origin of the Dhakeshwari temple is obscure. According to the popular legends, the original temple was built in 12th century by Ballal Sen, a Sena dynasty King based in Arakan (Myanmar) and the name of the city was coined after this temple. But the researchers found that the style of architecture of the temple cannot be a resemblance of that period. The temple complex has undergone repairs, renovation and rebuilding in its long years of existence and its present condition does not clearly show any of its original architectural characteristics. Nevertheless, it is certainly an essential part of the cultural heritage of Dhaka city.The temple consists of four adjoining rekha temples (buildings with a square sanctum on a raised platform with mouldings on the walls covered by tall pyramidal roofs of the typical curvilinear Bangla style. You are likely to find some long-haired sadhus (itinerant holy men) hanging around this colorful establishement.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Dhakeshwari temple.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="8">
            <name>Bara Katra and Choto Katra</name>
            <address>Lalbagh Road Dhaka</address>
            <detail>The two Mughal Katras in old Dhaka were originally built as caravanserais. Bara Katra was designed and built by Mughal emperor Shahjahan’s son Shah Shuja. Emperor Shah Shuja had initially wished to use this place as his Shahi Mahal (royal palace) but for unknown reasons changed his plan. Choto Katra was built in 1663 by Shayesta Kha, Subedar of Gujrat and later Bengal, chief commander of the army in the Golkunda battle after he arrived here. Now it remains in the most hideous and dilapidated state, its massive walls under cakes of mildew and its interior encroached by wretched, deplorable homes resembling slums, and small factories manufacturing soaps and tubes. Both the katras are private properties now, under negligence, in a stinky crowdy areas, lackin proper government attention and inaccessible to tourists. The picture was taken from the street. These katras are in short walkin distance from Chawkbazar square.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Bara Katra Choto Katra.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="9">
            <name>Ahsan Manjil</name>
            <address>Sadarghat kumartoli road,Dhaka</address>
            <detail>The Palace of Nawab (i.e. local ruler) of Dhaka is turned into a museum these days. Built on the bank of river Buriganga in Dhaka the pink majestic Ahsan Manzil is a part of nations cultural heritage. Nawabs of Dhaka contributed to the advancement of largely Muslim population of the East Bengal being stationed here. This palace now has 31 rooms 23 galleries displaying portraits, furniture. household articles and collections belonging to Nawabs' families. Interesting to visit are the 'andarmahal' (innerhouse / harem), 'rangmahal' (hall room). The pink colored palace has a huge dome at the top and wide staircase open to the river Buriganga in front. A century ago this was the prime location of residenc eof the rich people, all wanted to live by the river. The red colored additional building is used as a museum to display paintings, furniture and collections.The palace compound is open on all business days with nominal entrance fee.</detail>
            <open>Ahsan Manjil is close at Thursday. At Friday its open from 3-5, and any other days its open from 9-5. But at summer time, I meant after April, its used to be open till 6:00</open>
            <image>resource/Ahsan Manjil.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="10">
            <name>Bangladesh Postal Museum</name>
            <address>GPO, Dhaka</address>
            <detail>Inaugurated on January 30, 1985, the museum on an average gets about ten visitors a day. It is open everyday except on Fridays. No entrance fee is charged. The museum has only two rooms on the second floor of the GPO building and is unable to exhibit its entire collection due to the paucity of space as a recent report suggests.Stamps of different decades are among the attractions as well as, letterboxes, weighing scales, franking machines appeal to the visitors. The crown on top of the huge letterbox announces clearly that it belonged to the regime of Queen Victoria. The oldest weighing scale displayed at the museum was made around 1885. The old lanterns and candle cases are also a must-see.Letter boxes of various sizes and shapes used at different times are displayed. Those interested in stamp collecting can feast their eyes on the numerous stamps that had been issued throughout the years. An image of a 'Dak Harkara' (one who collects letters from one post office to the other) stands depicting one stage of the postal era.</detail>
            <open>Sunday – Thursday: from 9:00am - 4:00pm Weekly holiday: Friday-Saturday and all other listed government holidays</open>
            <image>resource/Bangladesh Postal Museum.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="11">
            <name>Suhrawardi Udyan</name>
            <address>Shabag Dhaka</address>
            <detail>A Popular Park. The oath of independence of Bangladesh was taken here and Father of the Nation Bangabandhu Sheik Mujibur Rahman gave clarion call for independence on this occasion on the 7th March 1971. The place is famous for its lush verdure and gentle breezes. Eternal Flame to enliven the memory of the martyrs of our Liberation war has been blown here recently.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Suhrawardi Udyan.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="12">
            <name>Shankhari Bazar</name>
            <address>old Dhaka</address>
            <detail>Shankhari Bazar an area, only a block away from the Buriganga River, stretches along a narrow lane, lined with thin slices of richly decorated brick buildings, built during the late Mughal or Colonial period. Despite rampant modifications, accretion, extension over time, even re-development, many still bear the testimony of a rich tradition.Besides the rich Shanka craft, a number of other traditional crafts like musical instruments, paper crafts, Shola-pith or crafts using jute straw and styrofoam sheet, clay statues for pujas and other religious purposes, and stone craft has made Shankhari Bazar unique.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Shankhari Bazar.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="13">
            <name>Baitul Mukarram</name>
            <address>Bangabandhu National Stadium Road,Paltan,Dhaka, Bangladesh</address>
            <detail>Baitul Mukarram is the national mosque of Bangladesh. Located at the heart of Dhaka, capital of Bangladesh, this mosque was founded in the 1960s. The mosque complex was designed by architect T Abdul Hussain Thariani. The National Mosque of Bangladesh has several modern architectural features, and at the same time it beautifully preserves the traditional principles of mosques architecture. Baitul Mukarram’s resemblance to the famous Ka'abah at Makkah makes this a unique mosque in Bangladesh.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Baitul Mukarram.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="14">
            <name>Ramna Park</name>
            <address>ramna Dhaka</address>
            <detail>Ramna Park is a large park and recreation area situtated near Shahbag, at the heart of Dhaka. The park, established originally by the Mughal emperors in 1610, was later developed by the British coloniar rulers and local Nawabs in the 19th Century. During British rule, experts from the London's Kew Garden were brought to plan the flowerbeds, the planting of beautiful and rare trees and the excavation of lakes. The serpentine lake where you can cruise by boat is also leased out for fishing. Tho however, it can assure you a pleasant walk you are advised not to be there too early in the morning and leave before dusk as a security precaution.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Ramna Park.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="15">
            <name>Dhanmondi Lake</name>
            <address>Dhanmondi,Dhaka</address>
            <detail>Constructed in the 60s, Dhanmondi Lake became part of Dhaka's history. Lakes and open spaces are a vital part of a modern healthy city. But there are not many parks or walking zone in this crowded city. However, Dhanmondi lake is surrounded by green area and modern apartment blocks have arrangement of paddle- boating in the lake, sipping tea-drinks and snack in the lake-side cafe and in the most part both sides of the lake has pedestrian side-walk. At one end of the lake, sits the Bangabondhu Memorial Museum. The lake has several pedestrian brdges to cross from one side to another.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Dhanmondi Lake.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="16">
            <name>Bangla Academy</name>
            <address>Shahbag,Dhaka</address>
            <detail>Bangla Academy , Bangladesh's national academy of arts and letters is an institution devoted to the development of language, literature and culture of our country. Bangla Academy building, formerly known as Burdwan House, contains an exclusive colonial style of late 19th and early 20th centuries. Originally a two storied building, it is rectangular in plan, the central bay holding the main entrance portico being projected out. A wide arcaded verandah runs in front of the building at both levels with balustrade railings. The arches are all semicircular which conform to the 19th century style. The wide verandahs not only act as shading devices but also protect the rooms from rain and provides easy circulation with adequate lighting and ventilation. The semicircular open balconies adds spice to the beauty of this simplistic building. After housing many government official since its establishment in 1905 as the seat of capital of newly established state of East Bengal and Assam, it was on December 3, 1955 that Burdwan House was declared the Bangla Academy and was renovated and another floor added in 1985. The site is worth of visit and convenently located in Dhaka University area, behind TSC.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Bangla Academy.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="17">
            <name>Seven Domed Mosque</name>
            <address>Mohammadpur, Dhaka</address>
            <detail>Satgumbad Mosque, translated in English as Seven Domed Mosque located in the Muhammadpur area of Dhaka city, the building exhibits seven domes - three over the prayer chamber and four over the corner towers. Hence it is known as Satgumbad (seven domed) Mosque.The mosque occupies the western end of a slightly raised masonry plinth 26.82m by 25.60m, which is enclosed by a low wall with a gateway in the middle of the eastern side. This arched gateway with flanking ornamental turrets is exactly in alignment with the central doorway of the mosque proper. The top of the gateway could be approached from either the north or the south by an ascending flight of steps.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Seven Domed Mosque.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="18">
            <name>Botanical Garden and National Zoo</name>
            <address>Mirpur-1, Dhaka</address>
            <detail>This is the most famous entertainment place of Dhaka city with area of 230 acres. The Zoo contains many native and non-native animals, It has more than 1,500 birds from 90 species, and visitors can expect to see peacocks, rhea, African grey parrots, cassowary, owls, ostrich, emus, teals, finches, babblers, owls, vultures, eagles and too many others to mention. Visitors are always fascinated by the crocodiles and snakes at Dhaka Zoo. A very rich museum is located here which provides many informative displays relating to the animals as well as the history of the zoo.This is located alongside of Mirpur National Zoo.It was built in 1961 with area of more than 100 acres. This garden collects and documents plant specimens from all over the country, as well as from far-off locations. The garden is categorized into fifty-seven sections and includes a cactus house, lily ponds, a lotus pond, six lakes, two nurseries, an orchid house, a tissue culture research center and comprehensive visitor facilities.</detail>
            <open>Entry Permits/Fees National Zoo: BDT 10 Animal Museum: BDT 2 Elephant ride: BDT 5 Horse ride: BDT 3 Botanical Garden: BDT 5 (Adult) BDT 2 (Child) BDT 3 (Study tour) Opening time National Zoo: 9:00 AM in Summer season ( 1st April to 30th September ) 8:00 AM in Winter season ( 1st October to 31th March ) Botanical Garden: 9:00 AM Closing time National Zoo: 6.00 PM in Summer season ( 1st April to 30th September ) 5:00 PM in Winter season ( 1st October to 31th March ) Botanical Garden: 5.00 PM During March to November 4:00 PM During December to February Holiday Sunday</open>
            <image>resource/Botanical Garden and National Zoo.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="19">
            <name>National Museum</name>
            <address>Shahbagh, Dhaka.</address>
            <detail>Situated at Shahbag, national museum contains artefacts dating back more than 2000 years from its Hundu, Buddhist and Sultanante and Mughal era. 2nd floor of the museum is the must see to see some very traditional 'palongko' (high legged bed) mostly used by Muslim and Hindu zaminders. A mat made of ivory is among the jewels the museum got to offer</detail>
            <open>Entry Permits/Fees Bangladeshi Citizens : BDT 10 Citizens of SAARC Countries : BDT 10 Other Foreign Citizens : BDT 75 Opening time April to September: 10:30 AM Friday remains open from 3:00 PM to 8:00 PM October to March: 09:30 AM *Friday remains open from 2:30 PM to 7:30 PM.Ramadan: 9.30 AM.Closing time April to September: 5:30 PM October to March: 4:30 PM Ramadan: 3.00 PM *In Ramadan Thursday and Friday  Holiday.Holiday Thrusday</open>
            <image>resource/National Museum.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="20">
            <name>Ramkrishna Math and Mission</name>
            <address>Tikatuli, Old Dhaka</address>
            <detail>A massive compount with impressive temple, this is the largest Hindu Temple and the adjacanfacilities in Dhaka. Photography is not allowed but entry is free to look and walk around.</detail>
            <open>Opens-1st April to 30th September Morning- 6 am to 12 pm (Afternoon) AND 4 pm to 9 pm at night 1st Oct to 31 March Morning- 6 am to 12 pm (Afternoon) AND 3.30 pm to 8.30 pm at night(REST OF THE TIME RAMKRISHNA MISSION WILL CLOSE)</open>
            <image>resource/Ramkrishna Math and Mission.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="21">
            <name>Baldah Garden</name>
            <address>Wari, Old Dhaka</address>
            <detail>Located at Wari, in the old part of Dhaka, it is set up by a private individual. The naturalist, philanthropist and poet Narendra Narayan Roy Chaudhury, landlord of the Estate of Baldah, established the garden on his own property in 1909. He collected different types of rare plants from almost all over the world from 1909 to 1940. The total area of the Baldah Garden covers 3.38 acres.To enjoy the floristic beauty of the garden a rest house – cum – amphitheatre, called the Joy House, was built in the garden. Many celebrities have visited it, including Nobel Laureate Rabindranath Tagore, whose poem Camelia was actually written while he was staying in this Joy House.The collection of the garden is classified into seven categories – orchids, cacti, conservatory plants, aquatic plants, arboretum, and miscellaneous flora. The garden has about 15,000 plants representing 672 species. Many of these are exotic and rare plants; perhaps the richest collection of exotic plants in the country is housed in the Baldah Garden. The flora of the garden represents collections from over 50 different countries.</detail>
            <open>Fee. BDT 5, Opening: 9am-5pm Sat-Thu, closed at lunch</open>
            <image>resource/Baldah Garden.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="22">
            <name>Sangsad Bhaban</name>
            <address></address>
            <detail>National Assembly Building is one of the majestic public buildings in the city is located at Sher-e-Bangla Nagar. It's an architectural masterpiece for which the nation is proud of.This was designed by American architect, Luis I Kahn. Born in a Jewish family in Estonia in 1901, he migrated to the USA along with his parents. His other distinctive works include Philips Exeter Academy Library, Bryn Mawr Dormitories, Yale Art Gallery, Salk Institute, Kimble Art Museum, Management Centre at Ahmedabad, India, Family Planning Centre, Nepal etc. His biggest as also the best work is the National Assembly complex at Dhaka.The mass of concrete lined with marble strips, the outer wall punctuated by pure geometrical openings and the dominating circular and rectangular concrete masses impart a supreme monumentality to the building quite suited to its noble functions. At the dead centre of the Assembly building is the main hall where MPs sit and the sessions of the parliament are held. There is not a single column in the whole building. Hollow columns that are parts of space enclosures have been adapted as structural supports. It is more like a concrete mass carefully carved and sculptured into a superbly functional entity. The construction material used is concrete and cast concrete forms both interior and exterior surfaces.</detail>
            <open>Entry Permits/Fees Need permission to Watch parliament activity.Not open for everyone.Holiday Saturday, Friday. But visitors can visit from outside</open>
            <image>resource/Sangsad Bhaban.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="23">
            <name>Zia Udyan</name>
            <address>Sher-e- Bangla Nagar, Dhaka</address>
            <detail>Better known as 'Chondrima Udyan' this park lies just behind the Parliament compound and accommodates the remains of late president Ziaur Rahman after being assasinated in a military coup in 1981. This place is one of the few areas in the city for a pleasant walk but also crowded during the weekends. There used to be a wooden hanging bridge which has been replaced by this newly construsted bridge. Come early morning/afternoon for better photography and fewer people. Stay in the evening to see the lighting and fountain.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Zia Udyan.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="24">
            <name>Buddhist Pagoda</name>
            <address>Kamalapur,Dhaka</address>
            <detail>Buddhism is the oldest religion of the area comprising Bangladesh that later dominated by Hinduism, Islam and Christinaity at different point of time. Usually native buddhists come from greater Chittagong area under different denominations. But Bengali buddhists are in the same branch of Srilankan Buddhism. However, the main 'pagoda' is located in Kamalapur area behind the area of main rail station, however, not within walkin distance. The compound has prayer room, dormitory for monks, a pond and separate prayer hall under Japanese financed arrangement. There is security at the gate and you be asked for your identity and purpose of visit. No entry fee tho</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Buddhist Pagoda.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="25">
            <name>Star Mosque</name>
            <address>Abdul Khairat Road, Armanitola,Old Dhaka, Dhaka</address>
            <detail>Star Mosque (Tara Masjid), a highly impressive ornamented mosque situated on the Abul Khairat Road, in Armanitola, was originally erected by a zamindar, Mirza Ghulam Pir, grandson of a rich aristocrat of the 18th century Dhaka, Mir Abu Sayeed.According to his name, the mosque was originally known as "Mosque of Mirza Shaheb". Later with much reconstruction by Ali Jan Bepari in 1926, the old structure had been completely masked. However, the remodelling and extensive renovation work was done very meticulously with the use of extremely delicate and richly coloured particles of earthern pots from Japan known popularly as "Chini-tikri". The use of glazed tiles in this mosque, its artistic ingenuity of exquisite fineness although an influence of Persian origin takes the pride of indigenous skill. In the centre of the wall a crescent and a star was made with the same Chini tikri.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Star Mosque.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="26">
            <name>Husaini Dalan</name>
            <address>old Dhaka</address>
            <detail>Husaini Dalan, a Shiite shrine in the old part of the city of dhaka, attributed to the Mughal Period. It is a common practice among the Shia community to build edifices to commemorate the martyrdom of al-Husain, at the battle of Karbala in Iraq on the tenth day of Muharram 61 AH (10 October 680 AD).Erected by one Sayyid Murad during the governorship of shah shuja, who, although himself a Sunni, was eager to preserve and patronise Shiite institutions. Traditions relate that Sayyid Murad, having seen al-Husain in a vision erecting a tazia khana (house of mourning), was inspired to raise the building, which he named Husaini Dalan. The original building may have been a small structure, expanded to its present form in later times. The east india company repaired it in 1807 and 1810, and a portion of the building was reconstructed after the earthquake of 1897.Although the Sunni sect is a majority in Bangladesh, there is a small number of muslims belonging to the Shia sect in Dhaka. During the first 10 days of Muharram, it becomes a center of mourning and religious celebration in old Dhaka. Both the Sunni and the Shia followers join the mourning, ending in the festival of Ashura when a great procession parades through the streets.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Husaini Dalan.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="27">
            <name>Novo Theatre</name>
            <address>Bijoj Sharani, Firmgate</address>
            <detail>Bangabandhu Sheikh Mujibur Rahman  Novo Theatre  is an attractive infrastructure with most modern architectureal view. It is located on Bijoy Sarani, Tejgaon at the centre of the Dhaka City having 5.46 acres of land. Besides planetarium show, Ride Simulator, 3-D film show and some scientific exhibits are displayed in Novo Theatre</detail>
            <open>Show Time:Saturday to Thursday (Wednesday Closed) : 11:00 AM ,  1:00 PM ,  3:00 PM , 5:00 PM Friday:   10:00 AM , 3:00 PM , 5:00 PM , 7:00 PM </open>
            <image>resource/Bangabandhu Sheikh Mujibur Rahman Novo Theatre.jpg</image>
        </place>
    </dhaka>
    <chittagong>
        <place id="1">
            <name>War Cemetery, Chittagong</name>
            <address>Dampara,No 19 Badsha Mia Chowdhury Road,Chittagong</address>
            <detail>Second World War warrior’s graveyards are in this Cemetery. There are 755 graves in this graveyard of the great warriors who died d in world war from1939 to 1945 in Chittagong areas. In this well-preservedcemetery at a quiet and picturesque place within the city lie buried in eternal peace over 700 soldiers froBritish, Australia, Canada, New Zealand, India, Myanmar, East and West Africa, The Netherlands and Japanwho laid down their lives on the Myanmar front during the World War II. Every year a number of touristscome here to visit this Cemetery</detail>
            <open>Open from 7.00 AM to 12.00 PM  and  2.00 PM to 5 PM</open>
            <image>resource/War Cemetery, Chittagong.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="2">
            <name>Bangladesh Railway Museums </name>
            <address>Pahartali, Chittagong, Bangladesh</address>
            <detail>It showcases a rich collection of relics, objects used in Bangladesh Railway's past eras: Bengal-Assam Railway (1942), Eastern Bengal Railway (1947) and Pakistan Railway (1961). The preserved artifacts mainly belong to mechanical, electrical, telecommunication, signal, traffic and engineering departments of the railway.Those include different types of lamps, lights, fans and bells, uniforms and accessories of station masters, signalling equipment, transmitters, analog telephone, monograms, track switches and railway sleepers. </detail>
            <open>No fee,the museum remains open to the visitors from 3:00pm to 5:00pm. Earlier, it remained open from 3:00pm to 6:00pm in summer while 3:00pm to 5:00pm in winter</open>
            <image>resource/Bangladesh Railway Museums.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="3">
            <name>Zia memorial Museum</name>
            <address>S.S. Khaled Road, Circuit House,Chittagong</address>
            <detail>Previously it was known as Circuit house where the former President of Bangladesh Zia-ur Rahman and one of the architects of the liberation war was killed by a group of disgruntled army personnel. To the memory of Zia,the Circuit house was declared as Zia Memorial museum .In this museum you can see late president Zia-urRahman’s daily usage materials</detail>
            <open>10.30am-4.30pm Sat-Wed, 3.30-7.30pm Fri </open>
            <image>resource/Zia memorial Museum.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="4">
            <name>Ethnological Museum</name>
            <address>Agrabad ,Chittagong</address>
            <detail>This museum located in Agrabad is a treasure house of a variety of tribal culture and heritage of Bangladesh</detail>
            <open>Opening hours 9am-5pm Tue-Sat  and  1.30-5pm Mon Oct-Mar, 10am-6pm Tue-Sat  and  1.30-6pm Mon Apr-Sep </open>
            <image>resource/Ethnological Museum.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="5">
            <name>Court Building Museum</name>
            <address>Court Building,Fairy Hill, Chittagong</address>
            <detail>Situated on the Fairy Hill, this building commands a panoramic bird's eye view of Chittagong. This had been the scene of intense activity during the independence War in 1971. A museum has been established here.</detail>
            <open>open from 10 am to 4 pm without holidays</open>
            <image>resource/Court Building Museum.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="6">
            <name>Shrine of Hazrat Bayezead Bostami</name>
            <address>Chittagong,Nasirabad</address>
            <detail>The shrine of this famous saint is situated in Chittagong. This great priest came to Chittagong in 10th Century to spread the religion of Islam. You can also visit the ancient rare variety of Turtles in the Dighi in the Shrine premises. This shrine attracts a large number of visitors and pilgrims. At its base is a large tank with several hundred tortoises. Tradition has it that these animals are the descendants of the evil spirits (genii) who were cast into this shape because they incurred the wrath of the great saint who visited the place about 1100 years age.</detail>
            <open>Open place</open>
            <image>resource/Shrine of Hazrat Bayezead Bostami.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="7">
            <name>Shrine of Shah Amanat</name>
            <address>Laldighi, Chittagong</address>
            <detail>The Shrine of Shah Amanat is another place of religious attraction, located in the heart of the town; the shrine is visited by hundreds of people everyday who pay homage to the memory of the saint.</detail>
            <open>Open palace </open>
            <image>resource/Shrine of Shah Amanat.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="8">
            <name>Fays Lake</name>
            <address>Pahartali, Chittagong</address>
            <detail>This lake is a natural beauty of Chittagong, where you can enjoy boating and also you can spend your leisure time in a serene atmosphere of lake and hills.</detail>
            <open>Only Entry fees: BDT 120 ( Adult ).Only Entry fees: BDT 60 ( Kids ).Opening time 10:30 AM Closing time Weekdays: 6.00 PM Weekend 7.00 PM </open>
            <image>resource/Fays Lake.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="9">
            <name>Patenga and Fouzdarhat Sea Beaches</name>
            <address>Patenga,chittagong</address>
            <detail>Patenga beach is about 22 km. from Chittagong and is approachable by a motorable road. On the way to the beach, one passes the Patenga Airport. Another ideal picnic spot is the Fouzdarhat sea-beach about 16 km. from Chittagong. Patenga sea beach is one of the major attractions of Chittagong for the tourists. Besides the sea beach, you can enjoy boating and river cruise in the River Karnaphuli. You can see the busy seaport activities here.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Patenga and Fouzdarhat Sea Beaches.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="10">
            <name>Port Area</name>
            <address>South east part of Chittagong </address>
            <detail>Located near the river mouth of the river Karnaphuli, the Chittagong port has a recorded history from 9th century. Today, this is the principal seaport of the country</detail>
            <open>It should be visited with the permission of the port authority </open>
            <image>resource/Port Area.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="11">
            <name>Sitakunda Chandranath Temple, Buddhist Monastery</name>
            <address>Sitakunda,chittagong</address>
            <detail>The famous Chandranath Temple  and  Buddhist temples are in Sitakundu, 37km for from Chittagong city. Famous among the many temples in this place, the Chandranath Temple and the Buddhist Temple has a footprint of Lord Buddha. These places particularly the hilltops are regarded as very sacred by the Buddhists and the Hindus. Siva-chaturdashi festival is held every year in February when thousands of pilgrims assemble for the celebrations, which last about ten days. There is a salt-water spring 5 km. to the north of Sitakunda, known as Labanakhya.You can enjoy the steer ridings to go to Chandranath’s temple by walking. It is situated on the top of the hill from where you can enjoy the beauty of the sea  and  also the hill areas</detail>
            <open>Open but day time good for visit</open>
            <image>resource/Sitakunda Chandranath Temple, Buddhist Monastery.jpg</image>
        </place>

        <place id="13">
            <name>Sitakunda Eco Park</name>
            <address>Sitakunda,chittagong</address>
            <detail>Sitakunda Eco Park (SEP), established in 2001, is situated under the Chittagong District. The botanical garden and eco-park area, comprising 808 ha, consists of a multitude of hills ranging from 25 meters to 400 meters. The popular religious site of the Chandranth Mondir (Temple) is also located on one of these hills, attracting many devotees and tourists. Home to many gushing waterfalls, the Eco Park was developed for the set purpose of conserving biodiversity and encouraging tourism.</detail>
            <open>Taka- 5.00/ Person.</open>
            <image>resource/Sitakunda Eco Park.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="14">
            <name>Parki Beach</name>
            <address>Anwara thana ,Southern Chittagong</address>
            <detail>Parki beach might be the next tourist attraction of Bangladesh, which is situated in Anwara thana under southern Chittagong region.The beach lies 16-17 km away from Chittagong city. As the beach is situated at the Karnafuli river channel, visitors can view both</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Parki Beach.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="15">
            <name>Chandraghona paper mill</name>
            <address>Chandraghona, Chittagong </address>
            <detail>Forty-eight kilometer from Chittagong, on the Kaptai Road is Chandraghona where one of the biggest paper mills in Asia is located. Close to the paper mill, there is a rayon factory, which produces synthetic fibers from bamboo.</detail>
            <open>Can be visited with permission of authority  </open>
            <image>resource/Chandraghona paper mill.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="16">
            <name>Cox's Bazar</name>
            <address>Cox’s  bazaar , Chittagong </address>
            <detail>Cox's Bazar is one of the most attractive tourist spots  and  the longest sea beach in the world (approx. 120 km long). Miles of golden sands, towering cliffs, surfing waves, rare conch shells, colorful pagodas, Buddhist temples and tribes, delightful seafood--this is Cox's Bazar, the tourist capital of Bangladesh.The warm shark free waters are good for bathing and swimming and  while the sandy beaches offer opportunities for sun-bathing.The beauty of the setting-sun behind the waves of the sea is simply captivating. Locally made cigars and handloom products of the tribal Rakhyne families are good buys.Every year lots of foreign  and  local tourist come here to spend their leisure in Cox’s Bazaar. Though the season is in winter but Cox's Bazar sea beach is crowded almost through out the year. Especially in winter season, it is hard to get an accommodation in the hotels if booking is not made earlier. If you are really adventurous and want to enjoy the wildness and madness of the ruff and tuff Sea you can come to Cox's bazar in the month of mid April, Sea continue its wildness till August; and its even more exotic if you come to Cox's Bazar in the time of depression of the Sea.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Cox's Bazar.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="17">
            <name>Himchori and Inani Beach</name>
            <address>Cox’s  bazaar , Chittagong</address>
            <detail>There are many attractions for the tourists around Cox’s Bazaar. From Cox’s Bazaar Sea shore, you can go to these places by jeep and it is really exotic to drive on the seashore. Himchori is famous for waterfall, though in the winter season it dwindles but during the rainy season it’s really a fabulous and full waterfall can be enjoyed. Inani beach is famous for the rock and coral boulders; you will find big coral boulders in this beach.You can plan a trip to Inani beach via Himchory for a half day or may be a full day sightseeing. Please take packet lunch with you.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Himchari National Park.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="18">
            <name>Moheshkhali Island</name>
            <address>Cox’s  bazaar , Chittagong</address>
            <detail>It is another attraction for the tourists who go to Cox’s Bazaar. An island off the coast of Cox's Bazar. It has an area of 268 square kilometers. Through the center of the island and along the eastern coastline rises, a range of low hills, 300 feet high; but the coast to the west and north is a low-lying treat, fringed by mangrove jungle. In the hills on the coast is built the shrine of Adinath, dedicated to Siva. By its side on the same hill is Buddhist Pagoda. You can go to this Island by local motorboat called trawler or by speedboat. By trawler, it takes an hour and a half and by speedboat, it takes only half an hour to reach this Island. You will find mangrove forests, hilly areas, salt field etc. This island is famous for Buddhist Temple and Pagoda; you can enjoy a full day sightseeing if you intend to visit Sonadia and some other Islands nearby. In the morning you can start for Moheskhali, spend time to watch Moheskhali’s tourist places, take lunch there and on return you can visit Sonadia and other nearby Islands where you can sea the live fishing  and  fishermen lifestyle; By the afternoon you can come back to Cox’s Bazaar.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Moheshkhali Island.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="19">
            <name>Sonadia Island</name>
            <address>Cox’s  bazaar , Chittagong</address>
            <detail>It is about seven kilometer of Cox's Bazar and about nine square kilometer in area. The western side of the island is sandy and different kinds of shells are found on the beach. Off the northern part of the island, there are beds of windowpane oysters. During winter, fisherman set up temporary camps on the island and Dries Sea fishes, which they catch from Sea.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Sonadia Island.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="20">
            <name>St. Martin’s Island</name>
            <address>Teknaf, Chittagong</address>
            <detail>St. Martins Island is the most beautiful Coral Island where you will find live corals. Its only 30 km from Teknaf and you can go there by local motorboat, tourist boats, or sea truck . This small coral island about 10km (6mi) southwest of the southern tip of the mainland is a tropical cliché, with beaches fringed with coconut palms and bountiful marine life. There’s nothing more strenuous to do here than soak up the rays, but it’s a clean and peaceful place without even a mosquito to disrupt your serenity.It’s possible to walk around the island in a day because it measures only 8 sq km (3 sq mi), shrinking to about 5 sq km (2 sq mi) during high tide. Most of island’s 5500 inhabitants live primarily from fishing, and between October and April fisher people from neighboring areas bring their catch to the island’s temporary wholesale market.In this Island, you will find the beautiful Coral reef and long Coral beach and lots of coconut trees. The local name of the coconut is Narikel and the original name of this Island is Narikel Jinjira is derived from that.Accommodation in St. Martins Island is limited, so it is advisable to book accommodation before you plan to go to this Island. Motel Nijhum is one of the best hotels in St. Martins Island. To book in Motel Nijhum, confirm you reservation from Dhaka. You will hardly get a chance to stay in this hotel if you are a sudden visitor of St. Martins Island. The other good hotels are Prashad Paradise  and  Sraboni Bilash.Booking of these hotels are also possible from Dhaka. All these three hotels are situated adjacent to Seashore. From these hotels lobby or veranda, you can enjoy the Sea. There are some other motels and hotels established in St. Martins Island.Overnight staying in St. Martins Island is really an exotic feeling where you will feel and listen the sound of Sea. If you are lucky enough then you can spend the exotic moonlit night at St. Martins Island. The beauty of Full moon in St. Martins Island cannot be expressed, if you are not there at that time.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/St. Martin Island.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="21">
            <name>Cheera-dwip</name>
            <address>Teknaf, Chittagong</address>
            <detail>a part of St. Martins Island but divided during tides. You can go to Cheera-dwip by walking.About two and a half hours walk from St. Martins Island or you can go there also by local motorboat or tourist boat. In that Island you will find the Corals - living and dead all over the Island. A small bush is there which in the only green part of Cheera-dwip, enhancing the beauty of this island. People do not live in this Island, so advisable for the tourists to go there early and come back by afternoon.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Cheera-dwip.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="22">
            <name>Nijhum Dwip</name>
            <address>Hatiya, Noakhali </address>
            <detail>This Island could be the next prime tourist spot after St. Martins Island. It’s a natural beauty of mangrove forests where you will find Dears of specific species and Monkeys. A huge numbers of migrated birds come in this Island in winter season, enhancing the beauty of this Island. The communication is not excellent but if some one wishes to bear the trouble to go to this Island, he will be enchant to see the beauty of this Island.You can go to this Island either from Dhaka or from Chittagong.From Chittagong first you will to go Hatia Island by Motor boat or Ship and from there you can go to Nijhum Island by local motor boat. From Dhaka you can go Tomzuddion by launch from Sadarghat launch terminal.From there you can go to Nijhum Island by local motorboat.Accommodation is very limited for the tourists in this Island. You can take foods from local restaurants but be careful about the quality of foods. If you can take prior permission for forest department then you can stay in forest rest house in Nijhum Island. Another possibility for accommodation is in District Parishod Guest house.If you take the permission from Thana administration (TNO) of Hatia you can also stay in the District Parishod Guest house. For the adventure seekers Nijhum Island could be one of the greatest experience of journey and it will be a memorable enjoyment to stay and pass some days in this isolated Island.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Nijhum DwipIsland.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="23">
            <name>The Aggameda Khyang, Cox's Bazar</name>
            <address>Cox’s  bazaar , Chittagong</address>
            <detail>Equally elaborate in plan, elevation and decoration is the Aggameda Khyang near the entrance to the Cox's Bazar town, which nestles at the foot of a hill under heavy cover of a stand of large trees. The main sanctuary-cum-monastery is carried on a series of round timber columns, which apart from accommodating the prayer chamber and an assembly hall, also is the repository of a large of small bronze Buddha imagesmostly of Burmese origin-- and some old manuscripts. Beyond the main khyang to the south, there is an elevated wooden pavilion and a smaller brick temple with a timber and corrugated metal root. Apart from bearing an inscription in Burmese over its entrance, the temple contains some large stucco and bronze Buddha images.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/The Aggameda Khyang, Cox's Bazar.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="24">
            <name>Teknaf Game Reserve and others</name>
            <address>teknaf Chittagong</address>
            <detail>The side of river Naf and the Bay of Bengal situate Teknaf Town, which is the southernmost tip of Bangladesh.It’s a real natural beauty of hills, forest  and  Naf River. Lots of Salt fields are there by the side of River Naf. Thereare natural waterfalls in Teknaf, which increases the beauty of nature.You can come to Teknaf from Cox’s bazaar by an exotic jeep drive besides the Seashore or you can go there by bus or Microbus by road. By road journey, it is 84 km from Cox’s Bazaar.You can enjoy shopping in the local market called Burmese Market where you will find all the Burmese  and  tribal hand made materials. Do not forget to see the Well of Ma-Thin – which tells a sad story of love. Myanmar is on the opposite bank of Naf River.Wild animals and birds are available but the most interesting thing is a journey on the river.Wide sandy beach in the backdrop of high hills with green forests is an enchanting scene never to be forgotten.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Teknaf Game Reserve and others.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="25">
            <name>Bongobondhu Safari Park, Dulahazra</name>
            <address>Chokoria Cox’s Bazar, Bangladesh</address>
            <detail>Bongobondhu Safari Park is one of the best safari park in south asia. It is the first safari park in our country. Bongobondhu Safari Park is situated dulahazara in cox’sbazar.It is the first Safari Park in Bangladesh. The nature of the forest is tropical evergreen and rich with Boilam,Garjan,Telsur and Chapalish along with herbs, shrubs and creepers.Bangobondhu Safari Park is a announced protected area where the animals are kept in fairly huge area with natural environment and visitors can easily see the animal when ever they visit by bus, jeep or on foot. This park was launched on the basis of South Asian model.</detail>
            <open>Visiting Time: From 9.00 am to 5.00 pm (Everyday)Entry fee : BDT  20  Foreigners BDT 350 </open>
            <image>resource/Bongobondhu Safari Park, Dulahazra.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="26">
            <name>Himchari National Park</name>
            <address>Cox’s Bazar, Chittagong </address>
            <detail>Himchari national park is a beautiful tropical rain forest around the South Asia. It formed the reserve forest areas of Bhangamura and Chainda blocks under the Cox’s Bazaar South Forest Division. this is Located about twielve km south from Cox’s bazar. The park was established in 1980. This place is managed by the Bangladesh  government for the local and the foreign tourist. The Park is also attractive for the biologist.</detail>
            <open>Visiting fee: 5tk only </open>
            <image>resource/Himchari National Park.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="27">
            <name>BARD</name>
            <address>Kotbari, Comilla</address>
            <detail>This is one of the main attractions in Comilla. This is one of the richest academic institutions for conducting research and action research; execute projects and pilot experimentation and imparting training in the diversified areas of rural development. The famous Comilla Model has been developed for sustained development. Besides academic excellence, the beautiful gardens and planned plantations of various trees are really enjoyable. You can also avail yourself of the facilities to organize seminar symposium and training in this complex .It is undoubtedly one of the good venue in Bangladesh where you can organize seminar, symposiums and workshops. BARD has excellent accommodation facilities for over 250 persons and its cafeteria provides quality foods. For one or two days refreshing you can go to BARD and spend some good time in a very secured and calm place.</detail>
            <open>bard.gov.bd for detail</open>
            <image>resource/BARD.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="28">
            <name>Lalmai Moinamoti and Shalbon Bihar</name>
            <address>Comilla</address>
            <detail>They are famous historical and archeological places around Comilla. These are a series of hillocks, where the Northern part is called Moinamoti and the Southern part is called Lalmai; and Shalbon Bihar is in the Middle of Lalmai and Moinamoti, which the was established in 8th century by King Buddadev. Salban Vihara, almost in the middle of the Mainarnati-Lalmai hill range consists of 115 cells, built around a spacious courtyard with cruciform temple in the centre facing its only gateway complex to the north resembling that of the Paharpur Monastery.Kotila Mura situated on a flattened hillock, about 5 km north of Salban Vihara inside the Comilla Cantonment is a picturesque Buddhist establishment. Here three stupas are found side by side representing the Buddhist "Trinity" or three jewels i.e. the Buddha, Dharma and Sangha.Charpatra Mura is an isolated small oblong shrine situated about 2.5 km. north-west of kotila Mura stupas.The only approach to the shrine is from the East through a gateway, which leads to a spacious hall.If you are in Comilla and already visited Lalmai, Moinamoti then don’t miss to go Moinamoti museum – where you will find the historical things found in Lalmai  and  Moinamoti of 7th  and  8th centuries. The Mainamati site Museum has a rich and varied collection of copper plates, gold and silver coins and 86 bronze objects. Over 150 bronze statues have been recovered mostly from the monastic cells, bronze stupas, stone sculptures and hundreds of terracotta plaques each measuring on an average of 9" high and 8" to 12" wide. Mainamati is only 114 km. from Dhaka City and is just a day's trip by road on way to Chittagong.Decidedly untypical of Bangladesh in topography and culture, the Chittagong Hill Tracts have steep jungle hills, Buddhist tribal peoples and relatively low-density population. The tracts are about 60km (37mi) east of Chittagong. The region comprises a mass of hills, ravines and cliffs covered with dense jungle, bamboo, creepers and shrubs, and have four main valleys formed by the Karnapuli, Feni, Shangu and Matamuhur rivers. Rangamati, a lush and verdant rural area belonging to the Chakma tribe, is open to visitors, as is Kaptai Lake. The lake, ringed by thick tropical and semi-evergreen forests, looks like nothing else in Bangladesh. While the lake itself is beautiful, the thatched fishing villages located on the lakeshore are what make a visit really special.Boats that visit the villages leave from Rangamati. Bring your swimming gear because you can take a plunge anywhere.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Lalmai Moinamoti and Shalbon Bihar.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="29">
            <name>War Cemetery, Comilla</name>
            <address>Moynamati War Cemetery Comilla District,Bangladesh</address>
            <detail>Second World War warrior’s graveyards are in this Cemetery. These graves in this cemetery of the enormous soldiers who died in the world war from1939 to 1945 in Comilla areas. In this well-preserved cemetery at a quiet and charming place within the city lie covered in everlasting tranquility over 400 defense force from British, India, Japan, and Myanmar, who laid down their lives on the Myanmar front for the duration of the World War II.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/War Cemetery, Comilla.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="30">
            <name>Rangamati</name>
            <address>Rangamati,Chittagong </address>
            <detail>If you don’t visit Rangamati you will not discover a big portion of natural beauties of Bangladesh. From Chittagong a 77 km. road amidst green fields and winding hills will take you to Rangamati. It is also connected by waterway from Kaptai.This is the only place to visit throughout the year. Rangamati expresses her full beauty in rainy season. Trees becoming greener, waterfalls are in full tide, the river Karnaphuli in her full wave in this season. If you already visited Rangamati in winter, we advice to go there again in monsoon; you will feel the difference of nature yourself.Parjatan holiday complex is the best place to stay in Rangamati. There are other hotels in Rangamati where you can stay. Boating is the prime attraction in Rangamati. You can go to Kaptai and also by Karnaphuli River you can go deep inside the hill areas where on the way you will find lots of natural waterfalls. If you wish you can take shower in the waterfall or you can swim in the river. By boat you can visit the tribal villages, King Chakma's (tribal) Palace that is called Chakma Rajbari, Rajbonbihar pagoda, Tribal museum etc. You can also enjoy the tribal handmade crafts if you go for shopping in the local market.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Rangamati.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="31">
            <name>Kaptai Lake, Rangamati</name>
            <address>Rangamati</address>
            <detail>Built in early sixties Kaptai Dam and the lake are the main attractions of Kaptai. If you are not visiting Kaptai separately then, don’t forget to go for a boating up to Kaptai on the Kaptai Lake while you go to Rangamati tour.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Kaptai Lake, Rangamati.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="32">
            <name>Shuvolong Falls, Rangamati</name>
            <address>Shuvolong, Rangamati </address>
            <detail>Shuvolong a place in Borokol sub district, located about 25kilometers (11kilometers – as the crow flies) away from Rangamati. There are few waterfalls in Shuvolong area with the largest one falling from as high as 300 feet. In the past several years, this place has turned into a tourist destination due to beautiful waterfalls and the nearby market. Shuvolong is easily accessible by speed boat or motor boats from Rangamati.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Shuvolong Falls, Rangamati.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="33">
            <name>Tribal Museum, Rangamati</name>
            <address>Rangamati </address>
            <detail>The museum is located near the entry point to the city. Established in 1978, it is run by the Tribal Cultural Institute. Traditional ornaments. costumes, potteries, musical instruments, armaments, paintings and photographs, old manuscripts, statues and ancient coins of various tribes are on display here.</detail>
            <open>open Saturday to Thursday excluding public holidays.</open>
            <image>resource/Tribal Museum, Rangamati.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="34">
            <name>Hanging Bridge, Rangamati </name>
            <address>Kaptai, Rangamati</address>
            <detail>This 335 feet long bridge across a portion of the Kaptai lake is an icon of Rangamati.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Hanging Bridge, Rangamati.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="35">
            <name>Kaptai National Park, Rangamati</name>
            <address>Rangamati</address>
            <detail>This forest reserve is located in the Karnafuly and Kaptai range. According to the government statistics some 50,000 people visits the national park every year as it provides some walking trails among the lush green forest. The animal species of Kaptai National park are deer, elephants, monkeys, fishing cats and birds. The Kaptai Forest Rest house, Kaptai Mukh Forest Rest House and several picnic spots are located here.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Kaptai National Park, Rangamati.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="36">
            <name>Rajban Bihar Pagoda, Rangamati</name>
            <address>Rangamati</address>
            <detail>An internationally known Buddhist Temple, where the spiritualist principal monk of Rajban Vihara, Shrimath Sadhana Nanda Mohasthabir(Ban Vante) lives.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Rajban Bihar Pagoda, Rangamati.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="37">
            <name>Peda Ting Ting, Rangamati </name>
            <address>Rangamati</address>
            <detail>A small island on the Kaptai Lake, few kilometres away from Rangamati. It is mostly known for its serenity. There are a few tourist accommodation facilities here and a tiny restaurant run by the locals. It offers foods ranging from traditional to indigenous delicacies.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Peda Ting Ting, Rangamati.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="38">
            <name>Chakma Royal Palace, Rangamati</name>
            <address>Rangamati</address>
            <detail>This is the palace of the present Chakma King. However, it is open to public for a visit.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Chakma Royal Palace, Rangamati.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="39">
            <name>DC Bungalow Area,Rangamati</name>
            <address>Rangamati</address>
            <detail>The District Commissioner’s Bungalow is located adjacent to the lake. There is a small light house and a shelter accessible to the public. This spot provides a nice view of the lake.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/DC Bungalow Area,Rangamati.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="40">
            <name>Khagrachari</name>
            <address>Khagrachari</address>
            <detail>Khagrachhari is the natural wild beauty of Bangladesh . places you can visit here is Hundred or more years old banyan tree: This hundred or more years old banyan tree is spreading almost 2 acres of area. Till Matiranga 10 number region of Khagrachari- Chittagong Road. You can go there by buses or chader gari. Will cost about 15/20 tk, and rest 1.5 km you have to go by foot or own vehicles.Nunchhori Debota Pond: The Nunchhori Tripura Village is about 13 km south of Porjoton motel, 4 km west from Maishkhali Army camp of Khagrachari – Rangamati road. Debota lake is almost 1500 feet above from there, on top of the peak of the Mountain.You can go by local bus or by chader gari till Maishchori Army camp. Rest 4-5 km you have to go by foot. If there is private car then it can go till the Tripura Village.Yonged Buddha Bihar: At Khagrachari town, 2 km far from Motel. You can go there by rickshaw.Panchari Brihot Buddha sculpture: Shantipur Arannya Kuthir is about 25 km south of Khagrachari town which is peripheral region. The largest Buddha sculpture of Bangladesh is situated here. Khagrachari to Panichari Local bus fare about 50 tk. The road is smooth and flat.Dighinala Manikker Dighi: This is situated at 21 km south of Khagrachari. You can also enjoy the Jhulonto Bridge, Buddha Bihar, Raja Manikker Dighi, Tribal culture, tradition and ancient standard of living. Khagrachari to Dighinala you have to go by bus or Chander gari.Shajek and Marissa Vally: This is endless natural beauty of green Mound. It’s hard to describe in words. You have to there by private or rented car.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Khagrachari.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="41">
            <name>Alutila and Mysterious bat Cave, Khagrachari</name>
            <address>Khagrachari</address>
            <detail>One can see the whole Khagrachhari town at a glance from the top of Alutilla. Alutilla is surrounded by deep forest, there is a dark cave with an inner dimension of approximately 100 meters long with a hill stream flowing right through. That will be a extraordinary experience for nature lovers for sure. If you go to Khagrachari don't miss the chance of visiting Alutila cave.First you have to go to Khagrachari town by bus. Alutila is in Chittagong Road, 5 Km away from the Parjatan motel. Local Buses or Chader gari, fares 15/20 tk.</detail>
            <open>Open but visiting the cave need some experienced guide </open>
            <image>resource/Alutila and Mysterious bat Cave, Khagrachari.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="42">
            <name>Hajachara waterfall</name>
            <address>Baghai Hat, Dighinala,  Khagrachari</address>
            <detail>Hajachara is one of the most beautiful waterfalls in Khagrachari. Hajachara is full of surprising natural beauty. If you visit Khagrachari don’t miss this majestic natural beauty.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Hajachara waterfall.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="43">
            <name>Terangtoi kalai waterfall</name>
            <address>Khagrachari</address>
            <detail>Richhang is another natural waterfall in Bangladesh. Not so wide and not as great as Jadepai or Nafakhum but is a beautiful waterfall for sure. This is the place of surprising natural beauty. Richhang is in Chittagong road the area of Hridoy member. Which is about 7 km from the Porjoton motel. 2 km shout from Alutila, 1.50 km from east from the main road. Local bus or Chader gari till Hridoy Member area. Rest 1.50 km you have to go by foot.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Terangtoi kalai waterfall.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="44">
            <name>Shoylo Prapat</name>
            <address>8km away from Bandarban town on the Bandarban Ruma road</address>
            <detail>This is one of the most famous and visited natural fall of Bangladesh. You can hear the purl of this fall throughout the year. The flow of this fall becomes vigorous during the rainy season. The water of this fall is so transparent and cool. It is a good source for drinking water and household use for the local bawm community. For availability of water here has grown 2/3 bawm village. It has become the main center for their economic activities.There is a small market for selling bawm  handicrafts, handloom  products  and  local  food  in shoylo prapat. You can see closely the struggling life of bawm community here in shoylo propat.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Shoylo Prapat.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="45">
            <name>Chimbuk</name>
            <address>Chimbuk is 26 kilometer away from Bandarban sadar</address>
            <detail>Chimbuk is the third highest mountain of Bangladesh. This is one of the most recognized familiar tourist spot just 26km away from Bandarban sadar. It's about 2500ft high above sea level. You will definitely be charmed having glimpses of the zigzag way heading to chimbuk, nilgiri respectively. While your jeep is moving through the various indigenous villages, their simplicity in human gestures will compel you to think about our predecessors struggles  to cope with to maintain existence. They are as generous as nature.Here nature nourishes her offspring with utmost love in her lap. When you are looking down from Chimbuk, it will get you the feelings of floating over the clouds. When it is a shiny day, you can see the shades of clouds over the hills. The huge horizon of zigzag hills seem waves of a see.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Chimbuk.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="46">
            <name>Boga Lake</name>
            <address>Ruma,Bandarban</address>
            <detail>This is the highest natural lake of Bangladesh. It is 3000fts above sea level  and  18km away from Ruma Sadar Upazilla. This lake has covered and area of 15acre. The colour of the water is blue. There are many mythological stories behind the creation of this lake. Thousands of tourists make their way to Bagalake every year, specially in the winter season. Small tribe community like Bawm, Khumi have localities beside the Baga lake. The communication to Baga lake becomes very difficult in the Rainy season.  The  road from Ruma to Baga lake is still under construction. You can go to Baga lake from Ruma by "Chander Gari" (public jeep) in winter season. But transportation is not always available there. There waiting lots of excitements and enthusiasm for you at Baga lake. You will certainly be amazed looking at the big rocks lying in and out of the Baga lake. You can have a camp fire beside the lake, that will be miraculous and unfaded memory in your life. So welcome to Baga lake to create a memory walks before you.</detail>
            <open>Open, for some security reason u need to entry your name in military check post and need to maintain some rules .</open>
            <image>resource/Boga Lake.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="47">
            <name>Nilgiri</name>
            <address>Nilgiri is 45km away from Bandarban sadar</address>
            <detail>Nilgiri is the highest tourist spot of Bangladesh. It is about 3500ft high and situated in Thanci upzilla. It is just 45km away from Bandarban sadar. Beside this spot you can see Mro villages. Their colorful culture and living style are surely an unexplored experience to you. In rainy season here creates a spectacular scenery, the whole spot is covered with the blanket of clouds. You can enjoy a cloudy experience. That is really awesome. Winter is waiting  for you with  it's  foggy gesture on the height.It is a nice place for campfire in this season. This foggy experience will remain crystal clear in your memory for decades. Sunrise and sunset are like an immense archive of glaring beauties in the summer. The sun is rising behind from the bottom of the hills illuminating the green hills and it is setting leaving behind a crepuscular dream for you. Its twilight with the breeze will ignite your Romanticism. You can also enjoy the serpentine course of Sangu River.  This is the most spectacular tourist spot in Bandarban and managed by Army brigade of Bandarban.</detail>
            <open>Open, for some security reason u need to entry your name in military check post and need to maintain some rules .</open>
            <image>resource/Nilgiri.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="48">
            <name>Rijuk Fall</name>
            <address>Ruma, Bandarban </address>
            <detail>When you are heading to Thanchi to Ruma by a boat you can have the glance of an exotic fall that is Rijuk Fall. Throughout the year this fall remains singing on the bank of Sango River. One can hardly control his impulses to get a shower under this fall. It has increased the surrounding beauty manifolds. It is much convenient to take an engine boat up to Rijuk. Remoteness doesn't always bear total seclusion as when you see untouched nature there, it  will  make you the  most  natural   and  very close to  your  heart strings. This  can happen with you at the sight of Rijuk Fall. Round the year you can go there but during the rainy season you can have the most rejuvenated glance of this fall. That's the refreshing season for the nature full of cool greenery making you feel harmony with nature.</detail>
            <open>Open, for some security reason u need to entry your name in military check post and need to maintain some rules .</open>
            <image>resource/Rijuk Fall.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="49">
            <name>Golden Temple</name>
            <address>Pulpara, Balaghata. It is just 4 kilometer away from Bandarban city</address>
            <detail>Its pagoda built on the top of the hills. It is regarded as one of the holy site for Buddhist pilgrims. Followers of Buddhism from different countries gather here to prey and visit. It's another name "Mohashukh Prarthona Purak Buddha Dhatu Chate". It has one of the greatest Buddha sculpture made during the contemporary period of Gautam Buddha. This  monastery  has been  built at  a cost of 100 million taka. It is one of the magnificent monasteries in the south East Asia. There is small pond in the monastery named "The Pond of ngels" on the top of a hill. From this you can have a total glance of Blaghata and its surrounding natural beauties. Every year a huge festival is arranged here.</detail>
            <open>It is always open for the devotees and remains open from 5 PM to 7PM  for the visitors. Each visitor is charge 10 taka for entrance.</open>
            <image>resource/Golden Temple.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="50">
            <name>Keokradong</name>
            <address>Ruma, Bandarban</address>
            <detail>Keokradong is the second highest mountain of Bangladesh. It is about 4332 ft high from the sea level. It is 30km away from the Ruma sadar Upazilla. During the winter season many adventurous tourists endeavor to visit this spectacular mountain. This remote hilly region is full of natural beauty. You can be overwhelmed at the first sight of this mountain. It is very close to the Myanmar border and you can see an endless courses of mountains and hills. This area is covered with dense forests full of beast and animals.</detail>
            <open>Open, for some security reason u need to entry your name in military check post and need to maintain some rules .</open>
            <image>resource/Keokradong.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="51">
            <name>Tahjingdong</name>
            <address>Ruma, Bandarbun</address>
            <detail>Tahjingdong is the highest mountain of  Bangladesh. According to local tribal language Tahjing means Great  and  Dong means Hill, combine expression is Great hill or Tahjingdong. The peak of this mountain is 4,300 ft above sea level. It is situated in Remakri Pangsha union under Ruma upazilla of Bandarban. It is 25 km away from the sadar upazilla. Thousands of tourist gather every year in Ruma upazilla to pay a visit of Tahjingdong.  Besides  this  mountain  there  are  various  tribal community whose versatilecultures and living  styles  are  so  nature  oriented.  Once  the  way  to Tahjingdong  was thought  invincible, but today a lot of tourists make this journey possible for the shake of beauty. Beauty is scattered everywhere on the way to Tahjingdong. During the rainy season its a real hardship to reach it. Specially in the winter season many tourists endeavour to reach it on foot as an adventure. At present one can reach close to the Keokradong by Chander Gari (Jeep). The remaining path has to be completed on foot. It is must for one to carry warm clothes during the winter season. In this respect walking habit will ease this tour.</detail>
            <open>check post and need to maintain some rules .</open>
            <image>resource/Tahjingdong.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="52">
            <name>Prantik Lake</name>
            <address>Keranihat-Bandarban road</address>
            <detail>With abundant natural beauties Prantik Lake lies in Holodia near the Keranihat-Bandarban road. It is 14km away from Bandarban town.  It requires 30mnt's drive. It covers an area of 2500acre. The management authority of this lake is LGED. This lake is surrounded by a good many varieties of trees. It has been regarded a natural habitat for different bird species. This lake is an ideal place for fishing. You can have fishing opportunity in this lake with the permission of the authority.It is an ideal place for excursion and family tour in solitude.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Prantik Lake.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="53">
            <name>Shangu River</name>
            <address>Bandarban</address>
            <detail>ShanguRiveris the integral part of the natural beauty of Bandarban. This river is flowing through the hills thousands of years. It is also an important route to communicate with Ruma  and Thanci upzilla. It has huge financial interests for the inhabitants of Bandarban. This river is widely used for transportation of agricultural and other necessary products for the people of remote community. Every year a huge quantity of logs and bamboo is carried through it.  In the winter season it almost becomes stagnant but in the rainy season you will be amazed to see the violent current of it. One must be fascinated with the beautifications scattered on the both sides of it. River cruise in Shangu is ecstatic and an exotic one. Nowhere in Bangladesh can you discover such a fusion of hills, forests, falls with a river. All the way you will be thrilled only. It is beyond one's imagination that nature is so candid and open here. Here birds are preaching your soul in the tranquil nature of the sermons to be blended with the innermost man in green. Shangu is like a chaplet of hills. You can feel truly during the boat cruise that nature is the greatest artist. On the way to Thanci you will see big rocks are showering in its flow. This is simply amazing.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Shangu River.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="54">
            <name>Upabon Parjatan</name>
            <address>Naikhongchari Upzila is near about 100 Kilometer away from Bandarban Sadar</address>
            <detail>Its a miraculous gift of nature in Nikhongchari. Here is a lake surrounded by forest. It is just 2 Kilometer away from Upzila sadar. There is a hanging bridge over the lake and it is longer than that of the Meghla. A lot of birds are twittering here and you will feel natural breeze also. It's an ideal place for passing time in solitude.  </detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Upabon Parjatan.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="55">
            <name>Mirinja Parjatan</name>
            <address>Lama Upzila is near about 70 Kilometer away from Bandarban Sadar</address>
            <detail>This is a fantastic tourist spot in Lama. It is situated at 16 Kilometer of Lama to Ali Kadam road. It is about 1500 fit high from sea level and an attracting spot for the tourists. You can watch Matamuhuri River and Lama Upazila from this spot. It is clean weather you can also watch the Bay of Bangle and Moheskhali Island. There is an Observation tower in this spot. There is a children park in Mirinja. You can walk up to Mirinja or can reach there by private vehicle.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Mirinja Parjatan.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="56">
            <name>Meghla Parjatan</name>
            <address>It is just 4 Kilometer away from Bandarban town</address>
            <detail>Meghla Porjatan Complex is the most visited spot by the tourists coming from all over the country tourist have the easiest access to it comparing other sites of Bandarban. It is in the contiguous area of the Bandarban hill district council on the gateway of Bandarban. At the bottom of the hills artificial lake has been made. It is just 4 Kilometer away from Bandarban town. Here is a great arrangement for the tourists for their amusement like Children Park,Boat Journey, Mini Zooand Hanging Bridge etc. Management authority of this tourist spot is office of the district commissioner of Bandarban. Communication to Meghla is smooth. That's why a lot of tourist makes the way to Meghla for celebrating their vacations.</detail>
            <open>Tk 30 fee</open>
            <image>resource/Meghla Parjatan.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="57">
            <name>Nilachal  and  Shuvronila</name>
            <address>It is just 5 KM. away from Bandarban town</address>
            <detail>This is the nearest tourist spot from Bandarban. It is situated at tiger Para. The spot is under joint management of district council  and  office of the district commission. It is near about 2000 fit above of sea level and 5 K.M away from the Bandarban town. From this you can have a total glimpse of Bandarban town and a vast landscape. In the rainy season you can be thrilled walking through the clouds. You can watch a golden twilight in the evening and also can enjoy an evergreen moonlight in the moonlit night. One can never imagine how it looks like during the winter season, it is just awesome all about the foggy morning. On the way to Nilachal, you will see some tribe villages with their raw natural expression. So welcome to Nilachal  and  Shuvronila</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Nilachal  and  Shuvronila.jpg</image>
        </place>
    </chittagong>
    <sylhet>
        <place id="1">
            <name>Tea Plantation</name>
            <address>Jaflong,Shylet</address>
            <detail>Tea is the heart of life in the Sylhet division. It produces over 55 million kg of tea annually from more than 150 tea estates spread over 40,000 hectares. You can stroll in the tea estate and wander a short way into the bushes and talk to the teapuckers and learn something about the processes that culminate into our morning tea.</detail>
            <open>Open at day</open>
            <image>resource/tea_plantation.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="2">
            <name>Madhabkunda Waterfall</name>
            <address>It is situated in Barlekha thana (subdistrict) in Moulvi Bazar District, Sylhet Division</address>
            <detail>Madhabkunda waterfall is one of the most beautiful waterfalls in the country. It is a large spot for the tourists and a major spot in Sylhet division. Lots of tourists and picnic parties come to Madhabkunda every day for their enjoyment.You can go to Madhabkunda from Sylhet by road or train. On the way you can see the greenish beauty of tea garden, the hills and the zigzag road through the hills will increase the joy of your journey. In Madhabkunda you will see the great waterfall – falls of million tons of water from 200 ft. height. There is a Parjatan Motel with a good restaurant for accommodation and food. There is also a district council Bunglow for night stay. Here you can enjoy adventurous feelings to stay in a jungle. All you need to have a prior booking for the bunglow from Moulovibazar Zilla Parishad Office.</detail>
            <open>Its free for everyone, no entry fee requires. This is open from morning to sun set. Staying at night time is not allowed by the authority.</open>
            <image>resource/Madhabkunda.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="3">
            <name>Jaflong</name>
            <address>It is located in Gowainghat Upazila of Sylhet District and situated at the border between Bangladesh and the Indian state of Meghalaya</address>
            <detail>Among the tourist spots in Sylhet division, the most attractive might be Jaflong. It’s about 60 km from Sylhet town and takes two hours’ drive to reach there. The aesthetics of Jaflong makes it a rare beauty among the whole country and of course the most beautiful place for the tourists in Sylhet. The scenic beauty amidst tea gardens and rate beauty of rolling stones from hills make you wonder why you have not visited this place before.Jaflong is situated besides the river Mari in the lap of Hill Khashia. The Mari river is coming from the great Himalayas, bringing million tons of stone boulders with its tide. You can watch the stone collection from the river in Jaflong as well as you can enjoy the boating in the river Mari. The beauty of Jaflong is enhanced a great deal where hills are greenish with the forests. In Jaflong you can see the lifestyle of tribal people, mainly of Khashia. If you intend to visit Jaflong it is advisable to start early in the morning from Sylhet so that you can comeback by evening covering the spots of nearby areas of Jaflong. The other tourist areas nearby Jaflong are Tamabil, Sripur and Jaintapur.</detail>
            <open>Its free for everyone, no entry fee requires. This is open from morning to sun set. Staying at night time is not allowed by the authority.</open>
            <image>resource/jaflong waterfall.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="4">
            <name>Sripur</name>
            <address>It is conveniently located only 7-8km from Jaflong on the same road to Sylhet.</address>
            <detail>Sripur is another beautiful tourist spot, the major feature is a number of waterfalls with great tide falling from the hills. After completion of visiting Jaflong you must visit Sripur on the way back to Sylhet.It’s only 78 km from Jaflong on the same road to Sylhet, a sub road entered into Sripur waterfall. Here you can see the stone collection and orange garden if you go inside Sripur crossing the hills.</detail>
            <open>Its free for everyone, no entry fee requires. This is open from morning to sun set. Staying at night time is not allowed by the authority.</open>
            <image>resource/sripur.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="5">
            <name>Tamabil</name>
            <address>Near Jaflong</address>
            <detail>Tamabil is the border area with India and is 05 km before Jaflong. If you intend to visit Shilong of India then you will have to cross this border by completing your customs formalities. To go to India you require valid Visa.</detail>
            <open>Its free for everyone, no entry fee requires. This is open from morning to sun set. Staying at night time is not allowed by the authority.</open>
            <image>resource/tamabil.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="6">
            <name>Jointapur’s Rajbari</name>
            <address>Jaintiapur is only 5 km. from Jaflong, After completing Sripur on the way back to Sylhet</address>
            <detail>Jointapur is only 5 km from Jaflong, a beautiful spot surrounded all over by tea gardens. At about 35 km northwest of Sylhet town, linked by rail, road and river. Jainta Rajbari was the palace of the king Jainta. However the palace is already damaged enormously but this place is still of a great interest to people , tourists due to the historic background of Jainta Kingdom and a large number of tourists visit here.A lots of picnic parties go to Jaintapur forests and also other areas of Jaflong, Sripur and Tamabil to enjoy a full day in the nature. So if you are planning to visit Jaflong you must cover up all these four places at a time and by the evening you come back to Sylhet for your night stay. Generally winter is the best season to visit Jaflong but if you want to enjoy the real beauty of wild waterfall then you should visit Jaflong in monsoon.</detail>
            <open>Its free for everyone, no entry fee requires. This is open from morning to sun set. Staying at night time is not allowed by the authority.</open>
            <image>resource/Jointapur_Rajbari.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="7">
            <name>Haors of Sunamgonj</name>
            <address>Situated below the foothills of the Himalayas, the vast wetlands Sunamganj is a district located in north-eastern Bangladesh within the Sylhet Division.</address>
            <detail>A Haor is a low lying depression on a floodplain, part of which dries during the drys eason. Haors are one of the main features of Sylhet division. They are mostly on Sunamganj district. Situated below the foothills of the Himalayas, the vast wetlands, locally known as ‘haors’, attract huge flocks of migratory birds in the winter months (OctoberMarch).Sunamganj wetland area is unspoiled and remains largely unexplored by tourists. Cruising through the shallow and clear waters is a special treat for birdwatchers and nature lovers alike. Varieties of rails, raptors, ducks, sandpipers and others congregate in these haors of Sunamganj are the most spectacular features here.
            </detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Haors of Sunamgonj.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="8">
            <name>Holy Shrine of Hazrat Shah Jalal</name>
            <address>dorgah moholla road, sylhet</address>
            <detail>One of the most visited places in Sylhet division is the holy Shrine of Hazrat Shah Jalal, a Mulim Sufi saint during the 14th century who came to Bangladesh to spread Islam. The place is of utmost interest of the tourists when they visit Sylhet, nobody normally misses its visit while visiting Sylhet. This is situated on the north of Sylhet city, off the airport road. The tomb of Hazrat Shah Jalal is located inside the shrine complex.It is one of the biggest pilgrimage sites in the country and a fascinating place to visit. Hazrat Shah Jalal’s sword and robes are preserved within the large new mosque, but are not on display. The tomb is covered with rich brocade, and at night the surrounding places are illuminated with candles.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/ShahJalal.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="9">
            <name>Holy Shrine of Hazrat Shah Paran</name>
            <address>About 8 km east of Sylhet, just off the highway to Jaintiapur, Sylhet</address>
            <detail>About 8 km east of Sylhet, just off the highway to Jaintapur, is the Shrine of Shah Paran in the tiny village of Shah Paran. It is a single dome mosque that attracts about 2000 pilgrims a day. This shrine is almost as popular as the shrine of the one of Shah Jalal.
            </detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Shah_Paran.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="10">
            <name>Srimongol</name>
            <address>Sreemangal Upazila (moulvibazar district) with an area 450.74 km2, is bounded by moulvibazar sadar upazila on the north, Tripura State (India) on the south, kamalganj upazila on the east, Sylhet District</address>
            <detail>The ‘tea capital’ of Bangladesh, a place blessed with tea gardens, hills and forests, Srimongal is a true beauty of nature. Within your eyesight you will find green throughout – greens of countless tea plants and leaves. It’s famous for the largest tea gardens of world covered by lush green carpet. One can have a look into the spectacular tea processing at Tea Research Institute situated here. Bangladesh produces and exports a large quantity of high quality tae every year to all over the world. Most of the tea estates in the country are in Srimongal. It is called “The land of two leaves and bud”.It is also called camellia, green carpet or Tea Mountain. There are a lot of tea estates including the largest one of the world. If you enter the tea estates the nice smells of tea leaves will enchant you and green beauty will carry your soul to elsewhere. There are some hotels in Srimongal where you can stay, but if you can manage to stay in the Tea garden that will give you a different, memorable experience. For that you will have to take the permission from the owner of any tea state.</detail>
            <open>Its free for everyone, no entry fee requires. This is open from morning to sun set. Staying at night time is not allowed by the authority.</open>
            <image>resource/srimangol.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="11">
            <name>Tribal Villages</name>
            <address>Sylhet</address>
            <detail>There are 11 Khasia villages called “Punji” and several Monipuri villages called “Para” scattered among the tea plantations spreading in Srimongal and Sylhet areas. Khasia villages are usually on hilltops surrounded by betel nut trees, which is their cash crop. In the Monipuri “Para” you can see the traditional weaving.Sylhet is well known for its wide variety of exquisite handicrafts. Wellknown Sylhet cane products such as chair, table, tea trays, flower vases, bags, shawls, share, napkin, bedcover and the exquisitely designed fine SitalPati (a kind of mattress having natural cooling effect) are colorful souvenirs. You can also buy the traditional crafts as souvenirs.For accommodation at Sylhet town, some reasonable good hotels are available. Resthouse accommodation at Srimongal and other places are also available for tourists.To cover all these places it will take 45 daystime. We have different set itineraries covering these areas. Please ask for them. In case none of those covers your subject or fulfill your interest, we shall be very happy to customize one especially for you upon request.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Tribal Villages.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="12">
            <name>Lawachhera National Park</name>
            <address>Located about 8 km east of Srimongal, Sylhet</address>
            <detail>This 1250 hectare park is a beautiful, evergreen tropical forest locally known as Shyamoli. This is one of the most important and well reserved forests in Bangladesh.It has the country’s largest population of critically endangered Hoolock gibbons – the subcontinent’s only ape species as well as a large variety of mammals, birds and orchids. Lawachhera is home to 19 mammal species including the capped langur, the delightful slow loris, orangebellied Himalayan squirrel and barking deer. Some 246 species of birds have been identified, which includes the bluebearded beeeater and the redbreasted trogon.</detail>
            <open>Its free for everyone, no entry fee requires. This is open from morning to sun set. Staying at night time is not allowed by the authority.</open>
            <image>resource/Lawachara National_Park.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="13">
            <name>Satchhari National Park</name>
            <address>This 243 hectare park is situated in Hobiganj, 60 km southwest of Srimongol, Sylhet</address>
            <detail>Though less popular than Lawachhera, it has a higher diversity of plants and animals and far less human disturbance. It has seven streams, the origin of the name “satchhari” came from these seven streams. A fair number of hoolock gibbons, fishing cats, phayre’slangur, jungle fowl, pygmy woodpeckers and oriental pied hornbills are the major feature of this park.</detail>
            <open>Its free for everyone, no entry fee requires. This is open from morning to sun set. Staying at night time is not allowed by the authority.</open>
            <image>resource/satchori-nationalpark-bd-tour1.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="14">
            <name>RemaKalenga Wildlife Sanctuary</name>
            <address>Located near Satchhari National Park, Sylhet</address>
            <detail>It is the country’s largest natural hill forest with a variety of plants, animals and birds and four different ethnic forest communities. If you visit Satchhari National Park, you must not miss this sanctuary.</detail>
            <open>Its free for everyone, no entry fee requires. This is open from morning to sun set. Staying at night time is not allowed by the authority.</open>
            <image>resource/Rema-Kalenga-map.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="15">
            <name>Limestone Lake of Tekerghat</name>
            <address>Tekerghat, Tahirpur, Sunamganj </address>
            <detail>The water of the lake is clear. This lake was created by quarrying the limestone. Exactly other side of the lake is India. People from India were having their bath at that side. Hill of that side having large boulders of limestone, but all belongs to India.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Limestone Lake of Tekerghat.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="16">
            <name>Barik Tila and Jadukata Nodi</name>
            <address>Tahirpur, Sunamganj.</address>
            <detail>Jadukata Nodi , another blue river from Bangladesh. The river is very wide, but due to winter it has became tiny. The mile long sandy bank of the river will give you a hint about the fierceness of the river at rainy season. There is a hillock beside the river, possibly 150 feet is the height. People says that as Barik Tila , Barikka Tila, etc. From the top of the hill, the people and the boats beside the river look very small.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Barik Tila and Jadukata Nodi.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="17">
            <name>Ratargul, A freshwater swamp forest</name>
            <address>Gowainghat, Sylhet </address>
            <detail>Its the only freshwater swamp forest from the Bangladesh. It means, the water is not salty like sundarban and part of the trees use to be under the water. And the trees from that forest are habituated in such a ways that they can even survive in water. In sundarban the water level is controlled by the high and low tides from the river, ocean. But in Ratargul the water is only controlled by the rainy season. At other seasons there will be hardly any water inside the forest. Those rainy season waters are in fact overflowed water from haor and rivers.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Ratargul, A freshwater swamp forest.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="18">
            <name>Bholagonj</name>
            <address>Dosh number point, Tuker Bazar, Sylhet  </address>
            <detail>The place is just beneath the Cherapunjee hills. River Dholai just entered at Bangladesh through Bholaganj. People used to harvest stone from there. The river, mountains of India, and the activities of people are very interesting there. There is a cable available for carrying stones.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Bholagonj.jpg</image>
        </place>
    </sylhet>
    <khulna>
        <place id="1">
            <name>Sundarban The Magical Mangrove</name>
            <address>Bagerhat, Shatkhira and Khulna district at Khulna Division</address>
            <detail>Sundarban is one of the best, one of the most attractive and fascinating places for the travelers from around the world, along with the local people from Bangladesh. Being the largest mangrove forest of the world and having an extra ordinary biodiversity, this forest is the point of interests for almost all adventurous travelers from Bangladesh and people from all around the world. The name Sundarban can be literally translated as “beautiful forest” in the Bengali language (Shundor, “beautiful” and ban, “forest”). The name may have been derived from the Sundari trees that found in Sundarbans in large numbers.About a third of the Sundarban Forest area is covered by a complex network of tidal creeks, mudflats and small islands, and the entire forest is subject to tidal inundation. Sundarban, Bangladesh’s only protection against tidal surges and annual cyclones, has the highest biodiversity of any mangrove forest in t e world.</detail>
            <open>Permission from the Divisional Forest Officer (DFO), Khulna is required to visit the forest</open>
            <image>resource/sundarban (2).jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="2">
            <name>Katka</name>
            <address>Katka is about 100 km from Mongla and about 150km from Khulna city.  Anyone can reach Katka From Khulna Forest Ghat and Mongla by water vessels like speedboats, sea truck, cabin cruisers, or launch, Khulna</address>
            <detail>Katka is one of Heritage sites in Sundarban. In Katka there is a wooden watching tower of 40 ft. high from where you can enjoy the scenic beauty of Sundarban.A beautiful sea beach is there is Katka you will enjoy while you are walking to go the beach from the watching tower. Thus, in Katka, you can enjoy the beach and the Magical Mangrove at the same time that leaves this place very special while you are on Sundarban. Also, a large variety of birds are on offer to watch and enjoy here.</detail>
            <open>Permission from the Divisional Forest Officer (DFO), Khulna is required to visit the forest. </open>
            <image>resource/kotka.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="3">
            <name>Hiron Point pic</name>
            <address>Sundarban, Khulna</address>
            <detail>Hiron Point is another world heritage site of Sundarban. You can enjoy the beauty of wildlife, specially dotted deer, walking and running in the forest.There are also two other Heritage sites in Sundarban one is Kochikhali and the other is Mandarbaria. At both of these places you will find deer and birds. If you lucky you can see the Great Royal Bengal Tiger in full. But if you are not that lucky, at least you will see the stepping of Great Royal Bengal Tiger here and there in these spots.</detail>
            <open>Permission from the Divisional Forest Officer (DFO), Khulna is required to visit the forest. </open>
            <image>resource/Hiron-Point-Sundarban2.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="4">
            <name>Karamjol</name>
            <address>Sundarban, Khulna</address>
            <detail>Karamjol is a forest station for the Rangers. Here you can see a deer breeding center. Here you can visit the outer portion of Sundarban forest areas.Sundarban is a heaven for bird watchers. In your Sundarban tour you will be able to see lots of varieties of birds. You can watch the fishing in the river by the fishermen, if you wish you can ask your tour operator to give a stopover in the fishermen villages to watch their lifestyle, see lots of animals like monkeys, various types of deer, foxes, crocodiles, snakes, and if you are lucky person you will be able to see the greatest mystery of Sundarban – The Royal Bengal Tiger. Sundarban is one of the main sources to collect pure honey, so you should not forget to buy some pure honey.</detail>
            <open>Permission from the Divisional Forest Officer (DFO), Khulna is required to visit the forest. </open>
            <image>resource/Karamjal.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="5">
            <name>Mongla</name>
            <address>The port is situated at the confluence of the Pashur River and the Mongla River. but it is now located 48 km south of Khulna city</address>
            <detail>Mongla Port, the second largest port of Bangladesh, is located 48 km south of Khulna town. The port was developed initially about 18 km up at Chalna, which was opened to foreign vessels as an anchorage on 11 December 1950. The anchorage was shifted to Mongla in 1954 as the place could accommodate seagoing vessels with greater draughts. The port of Mongla retained its name Chalna for a long period of time. Mongla is situated on the confluence of the rivers Pasur and Mongla at mouza Selabunia of Rampal upazila of Bagerhat district. In this country’s economy Mongla Port plays a vital role as it is a gateway of shipping, business for Bangladesh with all over the world. There are a good number of prawn hatcheries in Mongla.</detail>
            <open>Permission is required to visit</open>
            <image>resource/Mongla.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="6">
            <name>ShaitGombuj mosque</name>
            <address>It is located in Bagerhat district in southern Bangladesh which is in the division of Khulna. It is about 3 miles far from the main town of Bagerhat, Khulna Division</address>
            <detail>It is the largest and most magnificent traditional mosque in the country. Around the 60domed mosque are three other smaller, single domed mosques namely Bibi Begni’s Mosque, Chunakhola Mosque and Singar Mosque. About 2 km east of the ShaitGombuj mosque is the splendid Ronbijoypur Mosque. It has the largest dome in Bangladesh, spanning 11 meters and supported by 3 meters thick walls.On the western bank of the Thakur Dighi pond is the Ninedomed mosque. It has an impressive structure with mihrabs embellished with terracotta floral scrolls and foliage motifs, with a prominent chain and bell terracotta motif in the center. Just north of the 9domed mosque is the Zinda Pir Mosque.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/shat-gombuj-mosque.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="7">
            <name>Khan Jahan Ali’s mazhar/ tomb</name>
            <address>It is located in Bagerhat district in southern Bangladesh which is in the division of Khulna. It is about 3 miles far from the main town of Bagerhat, Khulna Division</address>
            <detail>A popular pilgrimage site in Bagerhat is the Khan Jahan Ali’s mazhar/ tomb. Khan Jahan Ali was one of the most respected men in Bangladeshi history and provided a significant support for Islam in Bangladesh. It is the only monument that has retained its original domed ceilings. The cenotaph at the entrance is covered with tiled of various colors and inscribed with Quranic verses. The outfront pond has a couple of sweet water crocodiles. There is also a singledomed mosque known as the Dargah Mosque.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Mazar-Khan-Jahan-Ali.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="8">
            <name>Vorot Rajar Deul</name>
            <address>Gourighona, Keshobpur, Jessore.</address>
            <detail>Vorot Vayna is an archaeological site that is still less known to us. In fact we even don't know much about this place. After discovering the site and also from the excavation, several valuable things were collected from here. By observing those things, experts are guessing this was built by the King Vorot which was was nearly around 2000 years from now. That time a lot of Buddhist people used to live around this place. Now a days local people know this place as Vorot Rajar Deul.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Vorot Rajar Deul.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="9">
            <name>Mirzanogor Hammamkhana</name>
            <address>Mirjanogor,Trimohini,Keshabpur,Jessore.</address>
            <detail>Mirzanogor Hammamkhanais a strange architecture if you do not know much about it. Cause only this edifice is existing now a days, and rest of its contemporary edifices are vanished. This is basically a bath room. A huge fort like mansion was available near this place.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Mirzanogor Hammamkhana.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="11">
            <name>Shekhpura Mosjid</name>
            <address>Keshabpur,Jessore,</address>
            <detail>This is an 18th century mosque that was built by a saint named Saiyad Pir Riaj Tulla. Our poet Michael Madhusudan Dutta used to learn the Persian Language here during his childhood.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Shekhpura Mosjid.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="12">
            <name>Modhu Polli of Poet Michael Madhusudan Dutta</name>
            <address>Sagordari,Keshobpur,Jessore.</address>
            <detail>Michael Madhusudan Dutta is a legendary poet in Bengali literature and considered as the father of Bengali Sonnet. It is nearly 150 he has departed from the earth, but his village and his house are still remaining there firmly. His father was a very rich lawyer from that time, and built this Elysian(as per that time) mansion at the village Sagordari. Now a days this house is converted as a museum that commemorates the poet, and opened for the public visitors.</detail>
            <open>15 taka per person.</open>
            <image>resource/Modhu Polli of Poet Michael Madhusudan Dutta.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="13">
            <name>Noongola Mosque</name>
            <address>Baro Bazar,  Kaliganj, Jhenaidah.</address>
            <detail>This mosque is a singled dome mosque and located at the village Mitha Pukur. Alike to the village name, this mosque is also known as Mitha pukur mosque.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Noongola Mosque.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="14">
            <name>Pir Pukur Mosque</name>
            <address>Baro Bazar,  Kaliganj, Jhenaidah.</address>
            <detail>This is another dilapidated mosque from the Barobazar.Only few remnant is available. This mosque is situated beside a large pond. Inside the mosque has a tin shaded building where people use to pray on a regular basis.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Pir Pukur Mosque.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="15">
            <name>Hasilbag Mosque</name>
            <address>Baro Bazar,  Kaliganj, Jhenaidah. </address>
            <detail>Actually the mosque is known as Sukur Mollik Mosque to the archaeological department, but local people know this as Hasilbag Mosque .Its a single domed mosque and the smallest one from the area.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Hasilbag Mosque.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="16">
            <name>Gorar Moshjid</name>
            <address>Baro Bazar,  Kaliganj, Jhenaidah. </address>
            <detail>Gorar Mosqueit is another mosque from the Barobazar. In my opinion, this is the most popular mosque among all from that ancient city. The name of the mosque came from Gorai, who was a dorbesh. It is assumed that Hosen Shah or his son Nosrat Shah built this mosque. The mosque has a large pond at the eastern side of it.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Gorar Moshjid.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="17">
            <name>Golakata Mosque at Barobazar</name>
            <address>Baro Bazar,  Kaliganj, Jhenaidah. </address>
            <detail>Golakata Moshjid is a square shaped mosque from Barobazar of Jhenaidah . Each side of the mosque is 25 ft in length. The mosque has exactly six domes in two rows at the top, and each of those are in same size and shape. The mosque has three doors at the eastern side of it.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Golakata Mosque at Barobazar.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="18">
            <name>Jor Bangla Mosque</name>
            <address>Baro Bazar,  Kaliganj, Jhenaidah. </address>
            <detail>Its a large single domed mosque placed over a high plinth. Initially it was built by Shah Sultan Mahmud Ibn Nusai possibly around 500/600 years back. But that one was destroyed completely. Recently the archaeology department constructed the mosque again and tried to give the original look and shape.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Jor Bangla Mosque.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="19">
            <name>Boluhar Baor</name>
            <address>Kotchadpur Upozila, Jhenaidah. </address>
            <detail>The whole Baor is around 11 kilometer in length. Also it is almost a circle in shape. Just a few, loke  500/600 meter short to form the circle. An island is available inside the circle which is connected to the mainland through tinny the mouth of the Baor . Name of the island is Kagmari . For this reason, lot of people know this Baor as Kagmari Baor. </detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Boluhar Baor.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="20">
            <name>Jugia Tati Para</name>
            <address>Jugia ,mazampur, Kushtia</address>
            <detail>"Tat Polli"(also known as "karigor para"), where the villagers used to make gamchha(kind of towel), lungi, etc using the hand looms.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Jugia Tati Para.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="21">
            <name>Jhaudia Shahi Mosque</name>
            <address>Jhaudia, Kushtia</address>
            <detail>A three dome mosque and its easily readable from the outlook of the mosque, that it was built couple of several hundred years before.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Jhaudia Shahi Mosque.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="22">
            <name>Shelaidaho Kuthibari Mela</name>
            <address>Kuthibari, Kumarkhali, Kushtia</address>
            <detail>To commemorate the birthday of the royal poet Rabindranath Thakur, the authority of the Kumarkhali Upazila of Kushtia District used to arrange a Mela at the kuthibari area.</detail>
            <open>Duration three days officially. But it remains for another seven days unofficially.</open>
            <image>resource/Shelaidaho Kuthibari Mela.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="23">
            <name>Shelaidaho kuthibari</name>
            <address>Shilaidah. This is under the Kumarkhali(Sub District of Kushtia)</address>
            <detail>This a nice white building. Kushtia was under the Nadia district during British period. Rabindranath Thakur used to visit this place several times to collect the royalty from the peasant of him. He inherited the Zamindari from his family.  There is a small museum inside the building.</detail>
            <open>10 taka</open>
            <image>resource/Shelaidaho_kuthibari.JPG</image>
        </place>
        <place id="24">
            <name>River Gorai and the Bridge</name>
            <address>Kumarkhali, Kushtia</address>
            <detail>Gorai bridge, which is also called "Mir Mosharaf Hossain Birdge" .It is very dry season. And I found it was really hard to find the sign of any water. After the river Padma, Gorai is the second largest river at the Kushtia. During the rainy season, Gorai is a ferocious. This is noticeably wide to proclaim this as a giant river.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/River Gorai and the Bridge.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="25">
            <name>Tomb of Fakir Lalon Shah</name>
            <address>Cheuria, Kumarkhali, </address>
            <detail>"Lalon Akhra" where the tomb of the great "Baul" Inside the premise of Lalon Akhra, there is a white tomb where the great baul sleeping. The tomb looks like it is made from wax. Also near the tomb area, you'll find several grave which are the contemporary baul of Lalon Shah, and some of them are the student or the followers of the Lalon Shah.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Tomb of Fakir Lalon Shah.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="26">
            <name>Tagore Lodge</name>
            <address>Kushtia</address>
            <detail>Tagore Lodge, the house that was used by the Rabindranath Thakur, the royal poet..Currently this is just a two stored small building. And each floor contains 3-4 rooms per floor.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Tagore Lodge.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="27">
            <name>S. M. Sultan Memorial</name>
            <address>Narail</address>
            <detail>S. M. Sultan  Was anlegendary artis .The whole premise of this memorial  is packed with lot of colorful flowering plants. After exploring those plants, and the grave nearby, we have entered inside the art gallery at where few of the works of the artist is displayed for the public visiting.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/S. M. Sultan Memorial.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="28">
            <name>Badha Ghat</name>
            <address>Narail</address>
            <detail>This ghat, beside the beautiful named river Chitra was built by the Jomidar of Narail, whose house was near from here(now vanished after having a vie with the era). Though it was built by a Jomidar, but local people used to call it as Rajbari Ghat.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Badha Ghat.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="29">
            <name>Tetulia Shahi Mosjid</name>
            <address>Tetulia,Upazila: Tala,District: Satkhira</address>
            <detail>This Tetulia Shahi Mosque was built by Jomidar Kazi Salamatullah Khan. Not sure about the exact date, but probably its more than two hundred years of old mosque.This is a 6 dome mosque having three domes in two rows. Total count of minarets are 20. Each corner is having 2 minarets, one is shorter and another is taller, total 8. Middle of each side is having another minarets, which means four sides are having total 4. At the top of each domes it is having one minaret, means another 6. Eastern side of the mosque having at the two additional minarets, which means total 20. Length of the minarets are varying. Few are much taller and can be seen from far distance over the trees.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Tetulia Shahi Mosjid.jpg</image>
        </place>
    </khulna>
    <rajshahi>
        <place id="1">
            <name>Mohasthangarh</name>
            <address>Mahasthangarh , Shibganj , Bogra.</address>
            <detail>Mohasthangarh is very interesting archaeological site of Bangladesh for tourist,it is the main attraction site of north Bengal.It was the capital of kingdon of the Moujo,the Gupta and the Sen dynasty. </detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Mohasthangarh.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="2">
            <name>Gokul Medh</name>
            <address>Gokul, Mahasthangar, Bogra.</address>
            <detail>The Gokul Medh is also known as "behular bashor ghor".its a part of the Mahasthangarh. Local people used to believe that this was the "bashor ghor" of Behula-Lakkhindar. Lakkhindar was cursed, and it was, he will die during the first night after his marriage by the bite of a deadly poisonous snake. That's why he has built a house and it was only a small hole, and through it only the needle can pass. But that couldn't save his life. But this myth doesn't have any authentication.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Gokul Medh.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="3">
            <name>The river korotoa</name>
            <address>Bogra</address>
            <detail>The river korotoa is a north bengal river that is originated from the great Himalaya like many other rivers of this country. This river entered Bangladesh through the Darjileeing of India, and after that it meandered through and caring the flows from many other rivers with it</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/The river korotoa.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="4">
            <name>Shila Devir Ghat</name>
            <address>Mahasthangarh , Shibganj , Bogra.</address>
            <detail>According to the legend, the Shila Devi was the beautiful daughter of the king Parshurama, some people used to say she was the sister of the King Porshurama. After the war with King Shah Sultan, Shila Devi jumped inside the water of the Korota river to save her honor, and drowned herself.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Shila Devir Ghat.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="5">
            <name>Govinda Vita</name>
            <address>Shibganj, opposite of the Mahastangarh Museum.</address>
            <detail>Govinda Vita is an archaeological spot from the great Mahasthangarh of Bogra.This place also has a very rich historical importance</detail>
            <open>This one is also close at Sunday, and open for other days from 9:00 to 5:00</open>
            <image>resource/Govinda Vita.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="6">
            <name>Mahasthan museum</name>
            <address>Mahasthan ,Shibganj ,Bogra</address>
            <detail>The museum is profound with numerous objects(status, coins, weapon, etc) those are found after the excavation from the archaeological spots around the mahastan.</detail>
            <open>The museum is closed at Sunday, and at Monday its open from 2:30 to 5:00. Other days its open from 10:00 to 5:00.</open>
            <image>resource/Mahasthan museum.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="7">
            <name>Varendra Research Museum</name>
            <address>Rajshahi town </address>
            <detail>This museum has a rich collection of objects of Mohenjodaro and also of 16th to 19th century A.D. This is devoted to the study of ancient history and culture. Its rich collections contain interesting objects of past Hindu, Buddhist and Muslim heritage. It is located at the heart of Rajshahi town and maintained by Rajshahi University authority. The year of its formal establishment is 1910 A.D.</detail>
            <open>Opening hours 10am-5pm Sat-Wed, 2.30-5pm Fri admission free</open>
            <image>resource/Varendra Research Museum.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="8">
            <name>Vasu Bihar</name>
            <address>Shibganj ,Bogra</address>
            <detail>This bihar is located at a remote place. There are three main architectures from the vihar. Two of them used by the Buddhist for the meditation, and it is now called university. And other one was for the prayer. A statue was at the plinth of the vihar.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Vasu Bihar.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="9">
            <name>Kherua Mosque</name>
            <address>Sherpur , Bogra</address>
            <detail>This mosque has three domes at the top of it. And the measurement of the mosque is 17x7.5. The mosque has four pillar at the four corners, and at the Eastern side it has three gates to allow the people to enter inside. The architectural observation avails that, it was build during Mughal era. The builder of the mosque is someone "Mirza Murad Khan Qakshal".</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Kherua Mosque.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="10">
            <name>Hinda Kosahba Shahi Mosque</name>
            <address>Khetlal,joypurhat</address>
            <detail>Hinda Mosque is a rectangular shaped mosque having a measurement of 49.5 x 22.5 feet. The mosque has five beautiful domes at the top. Five domes are for the five main bases/faiths of the religion Islam that people use to believe. The Dome at the middle is the larger one and other four around it are smaller and equal to each other. Mosque has a small pond at the north-west corner and a 40 feet tall minaret at the northern side.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Hinda Kosahba Shahi Mosque.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="11">
            <name>Baro Shibaloy  temple</name>
            <address>It located beside the Chhoto Jomuna riverof Bel-Amlavillage which is around 4 kilometer apart from the Joypurhat District</address>
            <detail>The name Baro Shibaloy means 12 houses of Lord Shiva. A rich Hindu person named Rijiblochon Mondol built this unique temple at the beginning of 19th century. These temples are arranged on the four sides of a Rectangle where each side of the rectangle contains 4 Shiva temples, and the temples at the corner of the rectangle is shared between two sides. In total 12 temples.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Baro Shibaloy  temple.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="12">
            <name>Lokma Jomidar Bari</name>
            <address>Koriya bazaar ,Pachbibi Upozila ,Joypurhat</address>
            <detail>The Jomidar of Lokma were Muslim in religion. Their main ruling portion was inside the India. Only Joypurhat and Pachbibi was from Bangladesh region. It is assumed that the Jomidar Bari was built somewhere around 200-300 years back. It was a 3 stored building and few portion is gone under the earth. It had around 17 rooms and most of the rooms are very dark at inside</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Lokma Jomidar Bari.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="13">
            <name>Paharput Buddha Bihar</name>
            <address>Paharpur union, Bodolgachhi Upazila, Naogaon</address>
            <detail>This massive Buddhist Bihara was probably built during the 8th or 9th century by the second king Sree Dhormopaldeb of Paal dynasty. It was active around 300 years for learning and religious researches. Our great Atish Dipankar was the chancellor of this Bihar during the 10th century. People from around the glob used to come here for sharing and learning knowledge</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Paharput Buddha Bihar.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="14">
            <name>Darosh Bari Madrasa</name>
            <address>Shibganj, Chapainawabganj</address>
            <detail>Darosh Bari Madrasa is possibly the oldest Madrasa of Bangladesh. According to the inscription that was found at the vicinity of the madrasa premise, it was built around 1500 AD, during the reign of Sultan Alauddin Hossen Shah. Now a days only few ruins are available.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Darosh Bari Madrasa.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="15">
            <name>Dighapatia Rajbari</name>
            <address>Nator</address>
            <detail>"Dighapatia Rajbari" is also known as "Uttara Gonobhobon". Inside the main rajbari, you'll find lots of statues which depict the culture of Greek. Also there are few black colored iron statues available too. Below are the few of the statues from the palace.</detail>
            <open>if you have the proper permission from the District Commissioner, only then you'll be allowed to enter inside the palace premise.</open>
            <image>resource/Dighapatia Rajbari.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="16">
            <name>Rani Bhobani's Palace</name>
            <address>Nator</address>
            <detail>You'll find lots of edifices inside the Rajbari premise. After 1984, for few days, the palace was used as a judge court of Natore. The Rajbari premise comprises of several large pond inside of it.There are  several numbers of temples or Mandirs inside the Rajbari premise.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Rani Bhobani's Palace.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="17">
            <name>Shah Shuja complex</name>
            <address>Shibganj, Chapainawabganj</address>
            <detail>It is unsure about the name of the builder, but from the design and architecture it is assumed that the period can be between somewhere 1639- 1660 AD. This structure is built beside a large pond.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Shah Shuja complex.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="18">
            <name>Daroshbari Moshjid</name>
            <address>Shibganj, Chapainawabganj </address>
            <detail>The sagacious peoples who have vast knowledge about archaeology believe that the mosque was built during 1479. It was the ruling period of Sultan Shams Uddin Yusuf Shah .Most of the parts of the mosque were dessicated with the time. Only few walls and the columns are standing, though those are after a through renovation.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Daroshbari Moshjid.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="19">
            <name>Khania Dighi Mosque</name>
            <address>Shibganj, Chapainawabganj</address>
            <detail>The mosque was built during 15 century. It has four domes, main dome is larger. Other threes are smaller. It has other names like Chamachika Mosjid, Rajbibi Mosjid.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Khania Dighi Mosque.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="20">
            <name>Chhoto Sona Mosque</name>
            <address>Shibganj, Chapainawabganj </address>
            <detail>The mosque is having total 15 domes at the top. Walls are built using thin brick, but after that it was wrapped with black stone to enhance the girth of the mosque's wall. There are four octagonal pillars available at the four corners of the mosque. The mosque wall is ornate with leafs, vines and similar kind of objects.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Chhoto Sona Mosque.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="21">
            <name>Dhunichawk Mosque</name>
            <address>Shibganj, Chapainawabganj </address>
            <detail>This is a six domed mosque. It was completely dilapidated and only few walls were available. But the government totally renovated this mosque recently. There is no road available to reach near to the mosque. You have to walk through the mango garden and beside the fields.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Dhunichawk Mosque.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="22">
            <name>Hardinge bridge</name>
            <address>Pakshey, Pabna</address>
            <detail>Hardinge bridge, its a rail bridge over the massive river Padma that was entirely built from the steel. This bridge is now around a hundred years of old. Possibly around at 1890, a plan was proposed for the bridge, and twenty years later the construction had begun, and finished it within only two years. Finally the transportation started during 1915. The bridge is named after the Hardingea governor of East India during 1910-1916. Length of the bridge is around two kilometer.</detail>
            <open>This bridge is not wide open for visitors, but with permission it can be done.</open>
            <image>resource/Hardinge bridge.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="23">
            <name>Cholon Beel</name>
            <address>Rajshai division</address>
            <detail>Cholon Beel is a vast water land located at the Northern part of Bangladesh. During the rainy season it's size increases further. This is the largest Beel from Bangladesh which is shared between four districts from Bangladesh. Natore, Sirajganj and Pabna are sharing the major portions, and Rajshahi is sharing very tiny amount.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Cholon Beel.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="24">
            <name>Puthia Rajbari  and Temples</name>
            <address>Puthia, Rajshahi</address>
            <detail>This place has a Rajbari and lot of different type of temples. The whole premise is surrounded by a lake which is acting as a boundary. The sites here are:Shib Mondir, Dol Moncho, Puthia Rajbari, Gobindo Mondir, Ahnik Mondir, Bidhobar Mondir, Boro Ahikrok Mondir, Gopal Mondir.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Puthia Rajbari  and Temples.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="25">
            <name>Bagha Moshjid</name>
            <address>It is located at he Bagha union of Rajshahi district. </address>
            <detail>Bagha is another antique mosque which was built during 1523. According to the reliable sources like Banglapedia, the mosque was built by an independent sultan, named Nashrat Shah.It has five doorways at the eastern side. Also the mosque is having an array of domes atop where each row of the array is having five domes.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Bagha Moshjid.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="26">
            <name>Kismat Maria Moshjid</name>
            <address>Pali, Shibpur Bazar, Rajshahi </address>
            <detail>It is totally unknown about any sort of historical information. No inscription available at the doorway or anywhere. Even our government doesn't have any document or info regarding this. To add insult to the injury, the local people can not remember anything about this mosque either. Its a total mystery.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Kismat Maria Moshjid.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="27">
            <name>Tarash Bazar</name>
            <address>Tarash Upozila, Sirajganj </address>
            <detail>You can visit here Roshik Ray Moth, Radha Gobinda Temple, Behular Kua, Behular Nouka and the Doi (card) mela of Tarash. The Mela held in the field beside an Old temple named Roshik Ray TempleEvery year during the 5th day of the Moon in Bengali Calendar month Magh the Mela use to start only for the single day. Its the day of Shoroshoti Puja.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Tarash Bazar.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="28">
            <name>Noborotno Mondir</name>
            <address>Noborotno Para, Hatikumrul Union, Ullapara Upozila, Sirajganj</address>
            <detail>This is a three stored temple where the first floor is the largest and the top one is the smallest floor of the temple. The temple is built over a high plinth. Its around 15 meter square shaped temple. Height of the temple is around 13 meter.</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Noborotno Mondir.jpg</image>
        </place>
    </rajshahi>
    <rangpur>
        <place id="1">
            <name>Ram Sagor</name>
            <address>Tejpur, Dinajpur </address>
            <detail>This Dighi was dug by the king Raja Ram Nath during 1750-1755 to resolve the water crisis of local people who were suffering from dearth. But now a days this is a famous tourist destination at Dinajpur</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Ram Sagor.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="2">
            <name>Nayabad Mosque</name>
            <address>Ramchandrapur Union, Kaharol Upozila, Dinajpur</address>
            <detail>According to the local people, to built the great Kantajew temple, lot of Muslims were came to this place. And those Muslim people built this archaic mosque for their own needs. That's why this mosque is contemporary to the Kantanagar Temple. Its a small mosque, and having three domes atop. 2-3 rows of people can be arranged inside during praying. But the mosque has a yard at the eastern side where additional people can stand during prayer. According to the inscription at doorway, the mosque was built somewhere around 1793 AD. Now a days a Madrasa is build at the eastern side of the mosque.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Nayabad Mosque.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="3">
            <name>Shopnopuri Amusement Park</name>
            <address>Aftabganj ,Nababganj,Dinajpur</address>
            <detail>Shopnopuri is a one of the attractive artificial tourist spots in North Bengal. This Amusement Park is divided into several parts. There are Rides, Zoo, Rest house, Garden, Lakes, Fish World, ‘Rongdhonu’ Art Gallery, ‘Moha Maya Indrojal’ and central Picnic center. One can find, Fish World with artificial fishes and various wet animals. Small Rides for activities. Animal Kingdom, for artificial statue of some animals like Amy, Flamingo, Dinosaur, Pegasus and many other animals. ‘Rongdhonu’ Art Gallery, for many different types of sculptures and paintings. At ‘Moha Maya Indrojal’, can enjoy magic. At Zoo, full of several kinds of animals. Anyone can enjoy his full day with family watching this artificial and natural beauties and activities. It is also an idle Picnic spot where lots of picnic parties come every year.</detail>
            <open>20 taka per person for entry , the park has several parts where you have to pay a little fee.</open>
            <image>resource/Shopnopuri Amusement Park.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="4">
            <name>Kantajew temple</name>
            <address>Kaharol Upzilla, Sondurpur, Dinajpur</address>
            <detail>Kantajew temple(Kantajew mandir) is one of the most attractive tourist spot from Dinajpur town. This mandir was built by "Maharaja Pran Nath", its construction started in 1722 C.E. and ended in 1752 C.E. This is the finest example of the terracotta from the country Bangladesh.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Kantajew temple.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="5">
            <name>Tajhan Rajbari or Rangpur Museum</name>
            <address>Rangpur</address>
            <detail>The museum is located south of the city, and was formerly a rajbari or a zamindar’s palace. Towards the end of the British Raj the building was decaying rapidly and abandoned. It was only during the year 2004 that the building was restored and converted to a museum. It houses magnificent art, coins and ancient inscriptions that are on display to all.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Tajhan Rajbari or Rangpur Museum.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="6">
            <name>Begum Rokeya Museum</name>
            <address>Rangpur</address>
            <detail>Begum Rokeya Museum is a women’s training center and museum, located in Pairabondh, the birthplace of the famous Begum Rokeya. It is a half hour drive away from the center of Rangpur.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Begum Rokeya Museum.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="7">
            <name>Kurigram Tourist Spots</name>
            <address>Kurigram is in Rangpur division. The district is on the bank of Dharala river.</address>
            <detail>Places to visit in this district are: Bhitarbandh Zamindar Bari (Nageshwari),   Chakir Poshar Beel (Rajarhat),  Dharla Bridge (Kurigram), Behular Char (Char Rajibpur), Canons of Panga Kingdom (preserved at the BDR Gate).  Image of Kali at Dasherhat, Images of Mangal Chandi, Joymoni Zamindar Bari , Kali Siddheshwari Mandir (Ulipur),  Kamakkha Devi,  Laksmi and Sattanarayan in front of the Bhetarbandh Zamindar Bari,  Phulsagar  (Phulbari),  Naodanga Zamindar Bari (Phulbari),  Naodanga Zamindar Bari and Mandir (Phulbari), Pangeshwari Mandir  and remnants of the Rajbari (Rajarhat),  Ramna Ghat (Chilmari),  Remnants of a mosque (Mughal period, 1176 AH) at Nayarhat (Rajarhat), Remnants of a mosque near Patweshwari Bazar (Mughal period),  Sindurmati Dighi (Rajarhat). Three domed mosque (Mughal period) at village Majider Par of Thanahat Union (Bhurangamari)</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Kurigram Tourist Spots.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="8">
            <name>Gaibandha District, places to visit.</name>
            <address>Gaibandha is in Northern of Bangladesh. It is a part of the Rangpur Division and located on the bank of Brahmaputra River</address>
            <detail>List of Top Tourist Spots / Places Baguria Tahshil (revenue) Office (nineteenth century), Bhabaniganj Post Office (1858), Bamandanga Zamindar Bari(1259) , Gaibandha Municipality park , Ghaghot River bank  ,Kashtha Kali Mandir at Bharatkhali, Mirer Bagan Shah Sultan Gazi Mosque at Gaibandha Sadar (1308), Naldanga Zamindar Bari  ,Palace of Raja Birat in Gobindaganj (743-800 AD)  ,Pourashava Bhaban , Shani Mondir ,Tomb of Pir Ibn Sharfuddin, Vardhan Kuthi in Gobindaganj upazila (17th century)</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Gaibandha District, places to visit.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="9">
            <name>Lalmonirhat Tourist Spots</name>
            <address>Lalmonirhat is in Rangpur division</address>
            <detail>List of Top Tourist Spots / Places for Visitors: Dharla Bridge at Mughalhat ,Hazrat Shah Sufi Muhammad Fazlur Rahman Tomb (known as Blind Hafez),Harano (lost) Mosque (8th century AH), Hussain Sarabor (dry pond) , Ijaradar Mosque, Kakina Rajbari, Kabi Bari (house and collections of poet Sheikh Fazlul Karim),Kutub Khana at Patgram, Khetu Mohammad Sarkar Bridge and Well  at Aditmari,Kakina Zamindar Bari Hawakhana Lalmonirhat District Museum  Mogalhat, Zero Point  ,‘Nag Lingam’ (rare variety of plant) ,Subadar Monsur Khan Mosque (known as Nidaria Mosque), Sindhumati dighi,Sindurmati at Lalmonirhat Sadar ,Tin Bigha Corridor and Burimari Land Port (Patgram) ,Tista Barrage (Hatibandha), Shalban (Hatibandha), Tista Railway Bridge at Lalmonirhat Sadar, Tusharbandhar Zamindar Bari,Tushbhandar Zamindar Bari (Kaliganj),Zamindar Mahima Ranjan Museum</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Lalmonirhat Tourist Spots.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="10">
            <name>Tourist Spots in Nilphamari</name>
            <address>Nilphamari is situated in Northern part of Bangladesh. It is a part of the Rangpur division.</address>
            <detail>List of Top Tourist Spots: Chini Mosque, Dighi (Nil Sadar Upazila), Dimla Rajbari, Garh (Fort) of Raja Dharmapal and his palace (eighteenth century, Jaldhaka) , Hari Dha, Leprosy Hospital , Nat Settlement (prison, 1871) , Neel Kuthi (Nilphamari Sadar Upazila), Nill-Sagor, Power Plant , Rma Paul Garh, Raja Harish Chandra palace (Ninth century, Jaldhaka upazila) , Railway Factory in Saidpur, Sayadpur Railway Factory, Sayadpur Air Port, Shahid Captain Bashar Gate , Shadhinata Monument, Tista Barrage (Dimla Upazila). Three domed Jami Mosque at Bherberi (eighteenth century, Kishoreganj upazila), Tomb of Hazrat Pir Mohiuddin (Kundupukur), Saidpur Church (1893), Uttara Export Processing Zone .</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Nilphamari.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="11">
            <name>Panchagarh Tourist Places</name>
            <address>Panchagarh is a district of Rangpur division and  northern part of Bangladesh.</address>
            <detail>Place to Visit:Banglabanda (Zero Point), Bhitaragara Maharaja lake Dighi (pond) at Bhitargarh,  Bhitar Garh,  Badeshari Temple, Boda temple, Box Museum (Government Women's College), Cheparajhara Paharabhanga Mosque (400 years old),  Debiganj Korthoa Bridge, Hosain Garh,  Kajala dighi,  Maidan Dighi,  Mughali killah (fort) at Chandan-bari,  Mirzapur Shahi Mosque (400 years old), Panchagarh Sugar Mills Ltd, Tomb of Arif Shah,  Vadeswari Temple, Baro Awliya Mazar.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Panchagarh.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="12">
            <name>Rangpur Tourist Spots and Attractions </name>
            <address>Rangpur is a district under Rangpur </address>
            <detail>Famous Tourist Attractions in Rangpur District: Ananda Moth in Kaunia, Benarashi Palli, Carmichael College. And they all are open places and no need to pay any fee </detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Rangpur Tourist Spots and Attractions.jpg</image>
        </place>
    </rangpur>
    <barisal>
        <place id="1">
            <name>Sujabad castle </name>
            <address>Barisal</address>
            <detail>From the bottom of Soil come the ruins. They found in the decay of debris brick part. In addition to an area of no interest. Often tourists of different parts of country and abroad came, see, find and took news about this place. What is viewed they are! At the top of the Bengali village.Homestead, farm crops, vegetation scenes. Above normal but below that there are some really cool! Son of Emperor Shahjahan prince Shah Sujara memorial palace.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Sujabad castle.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="2">
            <name>Kuakata sea beach</name>
            <address>Kuakata, Patuakhali</address>
            <detail>Kuakata (Sagar Kannya / Daughter of the Sea) sea beach is a white sandy beach. It is about 18 km long and 3.5km wide. It is one of the rarest places to see the full view of both sunrise and sunset from the same place or same position. This beach is surrounded by green trees and beside the beach there are many garden forest, like The Foyej Miyar Coconut Garden, Lembur Chor, Jhau bon, Gangamotir Chor etc. These gardens and forests are the most attracting part for the tourist. There are no quick sands in the beach. So you can frequently run, take bath, swim, and pick up cockle from the beach. There are two rivers, named Payra and Bishkhali are West of the beach and river named Agunmukha is East of the beach. It has also some wanderings sites like the Rakhain Polly, Shima Buddhu Bihar, Fatrar Chor,Rash Mela, Shutki Polli  that are enjoyable for the tourist.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Kuakata sea beach.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="3">
            <name>Gangamati Reserved Forest</name>
            <address>Kuakata, Patuakhali</address>
            <detail>Gangamati Reserved Forest is located on the eastern end of the beach of Kuakata. It’s an evergreen mangrove forest. Gongamotir Lake is the most attractive Open place in Gangamati Reserved Forest. It’s an additional part of Sundarbans with different kinds of trees and wild life.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Gangamati Reserved Forest.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="4">
            <name>Fatrar Chor</name>
            <address>Kuakata, Patuakhali</address>
            <detail>If you go to Kuakata you should go to Fatrar Chor. Locally its known as Fatrar Bon.It’s a part of Sundarbans. Mostly you will see here some Deer, Monkeys, Birds etc </detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Fatrar Chor.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="5">
            <name>Rajapur Saturia Palace</name>
            <address>Rajapur Upazilla , Jhalokathi</address>
            <detail>The palace was made about 3 hundred years ago. Besides this, there are many ponds, flower garden, three well designed Mughal building, Main gate are also at this palace area that has 100 acre land.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Rajapur Saturia Palace.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="6">
            <name>Mostofa Kamal memorial museum </name>
            <address>Alinagar union,Bhola</address>
            <detail>Bhola Island is the chest of the soldier hero Shahid Mostafa Kamal, in 1971; he killed by Pakistani army in the front wart. In his memorial government of People’s Republic of Bangladesh make Birshreshtha Mostofa Kamal memorial museum at his fatherland Moutupi mouja under Alinagar union in Bhola district.This museum is created as one storied building at in front of playground adjacent Alinagar high school.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Mostofa kamal museum.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="7">
            <name>Char Kukri Mukri </name>
            <address>Char Kukri-Mukri Island is in southern Charfession Upazilla under Bola District.</address>
            <detail>Char Kukri Mukri is the natural beauty that rises on the chest of Bhola. It is well-known as Dwip kanya too. Nature lover traveler loves its natural beauty of mangrove Forestry, Wildlife and sea. A lot of deer, cows, buffalo, monkeys and various species of wild animal and birds are live in the island</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Char Kukri Mukri.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="9">
            <name>Kali bari of poet Mukunda dash</name>
            <address>Situated in the town of Barisal beside Bogra Road south of Barisal connected both by air and road from Dhaka</address>
            <detail>There is the house of bird poet Mukunda Dash. Though he borned in Bikrampur but his father Guru Dayal was the massanger of Barisal court so, they sattled in Barisal</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Kali bari of poet Mukunda dash.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="10">
            <name>Sangkar Math</name>
            <address>south of Barisal</address>
            <detail>Beautiful temple with other nice places to visit around it. </detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Sangkar Math.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="11">
            <name>Oxford Mission Church </name>
            <address>This church situated in the town of Barisal beside Bogra Road south of Barisal.</address>
            <detail>The Oxford Mission Church, one of the most elegant looking churches in Bangladesh, is also a heritage structure of the country. This beautiful red brick church was established in 1903 from the sketch of Sister Edith. It was given a final shape by Father Strong. There are 13 ponds and Oxford Mission School on the compound. The structure is one of architectural brilliance, with many corridors. It has 40 archways that support the roof.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Oxford Mission Church.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="12">
            <name>Bangabandhu Park </name>
            <address>Located south of Barisal</address>
            <detail>The banda Road adjacent to Bangabandhu Park’s sewer has been turned into a beautiful lake. The garden adjacent to the lake have been more beautiful. Many different colored flowers around the sky, water-bound lake</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Bangabandhu Park.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="13">
            <name>Places to visit in Barisal </name>
            <address>Barisal</address>
            <detail>Aswini kumar town hall, BM collage university,  Bangladesh bank, Baptist church,  Badho-Vumi on river bank, Bell's Park,   Brass image of Manasa weighing three maunds (Char Bania Bari), Catholic church, Chakar collage, Charkella,  Dopdopia bridge on the river Kittonkhola,  Durgasagor Dighi at Madhabpasa babuganj upazila, Ebadullah Mosque,Girja Mahalla ,  Gutia mashjid/ Masque, Joint Mosque at Bhatikhana, Kali Bari of Mukunda Das, Kittonkhola River , Kasai Mosque, Muktijoddha Park, One domed Mosque (Kasba), Oxford Church, Rammohan Samadhi Mandir, Sujabad Kella, Sangram Kella, Shankar Math, Sharkal Fort, Sandha nadi/River, Sosan Ghat.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Places to visit in Barisal.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="14">
            <name>Bibi Chini Shahi Masque</name>
            <address>Betagi, Barguna</address>
            <detail>Bibichini Shahi Mosque was built at middle Sultane period in the 15th century the time of Ahmad Shah, Jalal al-Din’s son. Bibichini Shahi masjid is located at betagi in Bargun District. Shaw Neyamata was constructed this mosques in 1659. The village and the mosque named after the name of his daughter hayache bibicini. This Mosques is Thirty Three feet in length, width of Thirty Three feet, the walls Six feet wide. There are 3 grave beside mosque. The building are all constructed of brick</detail>
            <open>open</open>
            <image>resource/Bibi Chini Shahi Masque.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="15">
            <name>Places to visit in Barguna</name>
            <address>Barguna</address>
            <detail>Ashar Char, Buddhist temple (Taltali) and Buddhist Academy, Bibichini Shahi Mosque (Betagi), Donbunia, Fatrar Char, Haringhata Forest, Khoyra Mosque,  Laldiar Char and Sea Beach, Mazhir Char, Samudra-Bilash, Sonbunia, Sonakata Forest, Taltoli Rakhain Palli and Temple.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Places to visit in Barguna.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="16">
            <name>Monpura</name>
            <address>Bhola</address>
            <detail>Monpura is one of the famous nice island at Bhola in Bangladesh. Small Monpura island under charfashion subdistrict full of forest under forestry. The main attractions of monpura are Spotted deer, Monkey, python and lots of different kinds of Birds. The greens formed  by the Forest Department  about a decade ago and the natural beauty has turned coastal Monpura island  into an attractive tourist places. Animals were also released at same time. During winter season, lots of foreign birds come to the islands. The main attractive feature of this Island is one can see both sunrise and sunset from here</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Monpura.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="17">
            <name>Places To Visit In Bhola</name>
            <address>Bhola</address>
            <detail>Bank of Meghna, Bhola Shishu Park, Bhurhanuddin Abdul Jabbar College), Bir Sresta Mostafa Kamal,  Museum,(Alinagar union, Bhola Sadar), Bhorhanuddin helipad, Central Saheed Minar, Char Kukrimukri, Dhal Char, Graveyard of Tofayel Shah, Kathali Dafader Bari, Sadar Bhola, Kutuba Mia Bari, Burhanuddin, Bhola, Kheaghat Bridge, Kobi Mozammel Haque Town Hall, Manpura Island, Shabazpur Gas Field, Tulatuli.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Places To Visit In Bhola.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="18">
            <name>Kirtypasha Palace </name>
            <address>Kirtypasha village is located about 4/5 km. away from Jhalokathi town</address>
            <detail>Kirtypasha Palace was in the name of King Kirty Narayana. Ramjibon sen was the founder of Kirtypasha palace. Rohini Roy and Tapon Roy are the jewels of this family. Steamer dock, Rohiniganj is a contribution of Rohini Roy. With this, there is a hospital that is older than Jhalokathi district hospital. Co-mortal sign also is here. The grave of Rohini Roy re-made. Family Shiva mandir and a Shiva stratus here present</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Kirtypasha Palace.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="19">
            <name>Sonar char sea beach</name>
            <address>Patuakhali</address>
            <detail>In Galachipa there is a sea beach name Sonar Char. Galachipa is the sub district of Patuakhali district.If you visit the Sonar char sea beach, Sonar Char sea beach is as it is like to Kuakata. But the beach is very familiar sea beach. A lot of tourist come to the Sonar Char sea beach to see the both sunrise and sunset.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Sonar char sea beach.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="20">
            <name>Jhaubon at Kuakata</name>
            <address>Kuakata, patuakhali</address>
            <detail>Jhaubon is very beautiful place at Kuakata. Jhau bon is close to the sea beach. Jhau forest is created by Government initiative. Tourist or traveler can visit there by walking.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Jhaubon at Kuakata.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="21">
            <name>Gangamati Reserved Forest</name>
            <address>Kuakata Patuakhali</address>
            <detail>Gangamati Reserved Forest is an evergreen mangrove forest in the Kuakata Patuakhali Bangladesh. It is located on the eastern end of the beach of Kuakata. Distance from Gangamati Reserved Forest to Sundarban is one hour by speedboat. The best way to reach the Gangamati Reserved Forest is by foot or bike along the beach. Many of flag flying on the fishing boats can be seen at the coast when someone will walk beside the beach. The most attractive place at Gongamoti is the Gongamotir Lake.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Gangamati Reserved Forest.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="22">
            <name>Kuakata Buddhist Temple</name>
            <address>Four  kilometer away from Kuakata beach.</address>
            <detail>Kuakata Buddhist Statue is the biggest Buddhist Statue in South Asia.If a traveler visits Buddhist Temple he will see the statue of Goutom Buddha and also he will see the 200 years old wells. Traveler will find the about hundred year’s old ancient tradition and cultural heritage of traditional Rakhyne tribal families and Buddhist Temple.</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Kuakata Buddhist Temple.jpg</image>
        </place>
        <place id="23">
            <name>Pirojpur, spots to visit</name>
            <address>Pirojpur</address>
            <detail>Baleswar DC Park, Floating Vegetable Garden of Nazirpur, Guava Orchard of Nesharabad, Mothbaria Shapjora Kuthibari, Kumarkhali Kali Mandir , Majherchar, Momin Mosque, Madbaria, Pathorghata Sea Beach, Pirozpur University College, Remnants of Kaurikhara Zamindarbari, Rayerkathi Royal Palace and Temple, Sorupkathi Guava Garden(Largest in,  the country), The Mazar Of Sorsina Peer Saheb, Two Domed Mosque (Nesarabad).</detail>
            <open>Open</open>
            <image>resource/Pirojpur, spots to visit.jpg</image>
        </place>
    </barisal>
</divisions>
